<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-003">
  <num>KL-CY-2025-003</num>
  <heading>First Amendment to the 2018 Nepotism Prevention Act</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-04-22</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-04-12</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2025-003.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-003</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>At a duly called Session of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe held this 12th day of April, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe is a sovereign nation and has been so since time immemorial; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Tribe has the right to full enjoyment of the inherent powers of government, including self-determination and autonomy over internal affairs; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>	the Legislature is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(a) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>	the Kiowa Tribe enacted the NEPOTISM PREVENTION ACT OF 2018 in same year consistent with the determination of the Legislature that it is in the best interests of the Tribe to prohibit an employee or official of the Tribe from hiring a close relative (in the first degree), or to directly supervise a close relative, in order to ensure the integrity of the personnel and management systems, and to otherwise avoid any appearance of impropriety; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature has determined that additional clarifications are necessary to ensure the equitable application and integrity of measures to prevent nepotism and fraternization within the personnel infrastructures of the Tribe;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE IT BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Legislature hereby adopts the "First Amendment to the Nepotism Prevention Act of 2018."</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution KL-CY-2025-003, was duly voted upon by the Legislature on April 12, 2025, at a Legislative Regular Session XCVI-(96) with a vote of (6) in favor and (0) opposed, (0) abstaining, and (1) absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>LEGISLATURE - RESOLUTION NO. KL-CY-2025-003:</text>
    <text>SPONSOR: Cole DeLaune, District 4</text>
    <text>CO-SPONSOR(S):</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2025-003 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the 17<sup>th</sup>  day of April, 2025, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by the Constitution.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>______________________________</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text class="center">Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ]	VETO - RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ]	NO</text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution KL-CY-2025-0XX was overridden with Order KLO-CY-2025-0XX and duly voted upon by the Legislature on __________________, 2028, at a Legislative Order Session with a vote of ______ in favor and ______opposed, and _____ abstaining, _____Absent.  Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
  <section>
    <num>1.1</num>
    <heading>Short Title</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This enactment</cite> shall be known as the "FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE NEPOTISM PREVENTION ACT OF 2018."</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.2</num>
    <heading>Purpose</heading>
    <text>These amendments are enacted to bolster the existing provisions and aims of the NEPOTISM PREVENTION ACT of 2018 with clarifying language as well as to address the absence of anti-fraternization measures within Tribe code.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.3</num>
    <heading>Findings</heading>
    <text><cite path="1.3">Section 1.3 </cite>shall be amended as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The Legislature has enacted a law to create a system that provides for the fair and unbiased evaluation of candidates with respect to employment opportunities in the Tribe.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>The Legislature has determined that it is in the best interests of the Tribe to further define terms incorporated into existing statute.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Historically, the Legislature has received complaints about Directors and other Hiring Authorities with the Tribe staffing, onboarding and/or supervising Close Relatives, thereby creating the appearance of impropriety <em>as well as raising concerns regarding</em> the integrity and impartiality of personnel protocols.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>The Legislature <em>recognizes the imperative for </em>a system that provides for the fair and unbiased evaluation of candidates for employment opportunities in the Tribe.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.4</num>
    <heading>Definitions</heading>
    <text><cite path="1.4">Section 1.4 </cite>shall be amended as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>"Close Relative" shall mean any of the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>A family relative in the first degree, including mothers/fathers, brothers/sisters, sons/daughters, husbands/wives, aunts/uncles, nephews/nieces, or first cousins.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Mothers-, fathers-, daughters-, sons-, brothers-, and sisters-in-law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Stepchildren and stepparents affiliated via legal or common law marriage, or by virtue of formal domestic partnership.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Family relatives of direct lineal ascendency or descendancy in the second degree.</text>
      </para>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>"Hiring Authority" shall mean any person or persons, <em>including all elected officials</em>, <em>with the formally recognized</em> authority to make a hiring decision <em>for a role under their respective immediate and direct supervision.</em></text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.5</num>
    <heading>Hiring</heading>
    <text><cite path="1.5">Section 1.5 </cite>shall be amended as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>. 	Upon review of the candidates applying for a job with the Tribe, the Hiring Authority shall not make any decision to hire a Close Relative.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>. 	For all new openings and applicable hires after the reaffirmation of <cite path="">this Act</cite>, the Hiring Authority shall not consider any Close Relative <em>as a</em> candidate for employment <em>under their direct and immediate supervision</em>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>. 	<em>Hiring Authorities vested with supervisory purview over multiple personnel within a single Tribe Department shall recuse themselves from hiring decisions for Department roles not under their immediate supervision if a Close Relative is a candidate for any of same roles.</em></text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.6</num>
    <heading>Supervision and Management of an Existing Employee who is a Close Relative</heading>
    <text><cite path="1.6">Section 1.6 </cite>shall be amended as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>No Executive Branch official or employee of the Tribe shall directly manage or supervise a Close Relative.  <em>Nor shall officials or employees of the Legislative or Judicial Branches directly manage or supervise a Close Relative.</em></text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text>Upon the <em>reaffirmation</em> of <cite path="">this Act</cite>, any employee who is serving as a manger or supervisor of a Close Relative shall notify the Chairman, Tribe Executive Director, and Human Resources in writing; same parties shall take steps to reorganize the line of authority between the manager or supervisor and the employee to eliminate any direct management or supervision of a Close Relative, notwithstanding any law or policy to the contrary.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.7</num>
    <heading>Other Prohibitions</heading>
    <text><cite path="1.7">Section 1.7 </cite>shall be added by amendment as follows:</text>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>No Hiring Authority shall make a decision to hire a candidate for employment under their direct and immediate supervision with whom they are engaged in sexual conduct and/or a romantic relationship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(d)</num>
      <text>Hiring Authorities vested with supervisory purview over multiple personnel within a single Tribe Department shall recuse themselves from hiring decisions for Department roles not under their immediate supervision if any person or persons with whom they are engaged in sexual and/or romantic conduct are candidates for any such roles.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(e)</num>
      <text>Neither elected/appointed officials nor employees of the Executive, Legislative, or Judicial Branches shall directly manage or supervise a person or persons with whom they are engaged in sexual and/or romantic conduct.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(f)</num>
      <text>Engagement in any sexual contact with a subordinate under their respective direct management or supervision by any official or employee of the Executive, Legislative, and/or Judicial Branches shall be prohibited by <cite path="">this statute</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
</document>
