<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-006">
  <num>KL-CY-2025-006</num>
  <heading>Kiowa Tribe Executive Appointments for Elected Vacancies Act of 2025.</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-04-22</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-04-12</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2025-006.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-006</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe is a sovereign nation and has been so since time immemorial; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Tribe has the right to full enjoyment of the inherent powers of government, including self-determination and autonomy over internal affairs; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> qualified voters of the Tribe ratified the Kiowa Constitution on April 17, 2017, as "the supreme law of the land"; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> same Constitution establishes the structure of the Kiowa Government, including separation of powers among four lateral branches as well as the subordinance in the Executive Branch of the office of Vice-Chairman, the occupant of which serves at the pleasure of the Chairman of the Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Constitution delineates protocols for the dismissal of a Vice-Chairman consistent with the judgment of the Chairman; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article XII, Section 9 </cite>of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> asserts, "Any vacancy in the Office of Vice-Chairman shall by filled by appointment by the Chairman"; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> same Article fails to impose any temporal mandates on the prescribed appointment process; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(a)</cite>; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Constitution does not provide for a line of Executive Branch succession beyond assumption of the Office of Chairman by a Vice-Chairman; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Office of the Vice-Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe has remained vacant since September 2024; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> it is improbable that either the authors of or the voters who approved <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> intended for a vacancy in the Office of Vice-Chairman to persist in perpetuity; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> provides for appointments by the Chairman to legislative offices, subject to confirmation of nominees by the Legislature, when vacancies arise in same offices with less than six months remaining in a term; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> by contrast, when applicable, <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> obligates the Election Commission to conduct a Special Election to fill analogous vacancies for other elected offices within a span of forty-five days; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature acknowledges and respects <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the constitution</cite>al authority of the Chairman to select a Vice-Chairman sans legislative confirmation; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature has determined that statutory codification of a clear timeline for appointment of a Vice-Chairman in the event of a vacancy in same office is necessary in the interests of developing organizational protections against the possibility of a constitutional crisis due to limitations of existing constitutional provisions for Executive succession;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Legislature hereby enacts "Executive Appointments for Elected Vacancies Act of 2025."</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution KL-CY-2025-006, was duly voted upon by the Legislature on April 12, 2025, at a Legislative Regular Session XCVI-(96) with a vote of (6) in favor and (0) opposed, (0) abstaining, and (1) absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>LEGISLATURE - RESOLUTION NO. KL-CY-2025-006:</text>
    <text>SPONSOR: Cole DeLaune, District 4</text>
    <text>CO-SPONSOR(S):</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td data-text-align="center">X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td data-text-align="center">X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2025-006 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the 17<sup>th</sup>  day of April, 2025, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by the Constitution.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>______________________________</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text class="center">Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ]	VETO - RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ]	NO</text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution KL-CY-2025-006 was overridden with Order KLO-CY-2025-0XX and duly voted upon by the Legislature on __________________, 2025, at a Legislative Order Session with a vote of ______ in favor and ______opposed, and _____ abstaining, _____Absent.  Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
  <section>
    <num>1.1</num>
    <heading>Short Title</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This enactment</cite> shall be known as the "Executive Appointments for Elected Vacancies Act of 2025".</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.2</num>
    <heading>Purpose</heading>
    <text>These provisions are enacted to define an unambiguous timeline in the event that circumstances require the Chairman to fill a vacancy in the Office of Vice-Chairman or in the Office of Legislator by appointment.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.3</num>
    <heading>Findings</heading>
    <text>The Legislature hereby finds and declares that:</text>
    <para>
      <num>a.</num>
      <text>As of April 2025, the Office of Vice-Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe has remained vacant for no less than six months.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>b.</num>
      <text><cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">The Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite> provides for no succession in Executive Branch leadership beyond the assumption of the Chairmanship by the Vice-Chairman in the event of a vacancy in same Chairmanship.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>c.</num>
      <text>A sustained vacancy in the Office of Vice-Chairman imperils Tribe operations as well as the interests and constitutional rights of Tribe Members at large.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>d.</num>
      <text>Codification in statute of timeline mandates for appointments delegated to the Chairman by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> shall be consistent with the provisions of same Constitution for conducting special elections upon legislative vacancies.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.4</num>
    <heading>Timetables in Record</heading>
    <para>
      <num>e.</num>
      <text>Upon a vacancy in the Office of Vice-Chairman, the Chairman shall fill same vacancy by appointment within forty-five (45) calendar days by ensuring that his or her respective selection for Vice-Chairman is sworn into office by 11:59 p.m. of the forty-fifth (45<sup>th</sup>) day consistent with the provisions of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> for the administration of the Oath sworn by all elected officials of the Tribe.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>f.</num>
      <text>The Chairman shall publicly announce the name of his or her respective selection for Vice-Chairman through official Tribe media applications including, by way of example and without limitation, social media platforms and/or radio programming no later than 11:59 p.m. on the forty-fifth (45<sup>th) </sup>calendar day after a vacancy in the Office of Vice-Chairman.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>g.</num>
      <text>The forty-five-day timetable shall commence with Day 1 on the same calendar day as death or resignation in the event that a vacancy occurs due to such circumstances in the Office of Vice-Chairman.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>h.</num>
      <text>Should a vacancy arise in the Office of Vice-Chairman due to a recall vote conducted by Special Election, the forty-five-day timetable shall commence with Day 1 on the same calendar day as results of the Special Election are formalized as official by the Election Commission in accordance with the provisions of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and Tribe law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>i.</num>
      <text>Should a vacancy arise in the Office of Vice-Chairman due to impeachment and removal by the Legislature, the forty-five-day timetable shall commence with Day 1 on the same calendar day as the issuance of the Legislative Order effecting same removal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>j.</num>
      <text>Should a vacancy occur in the Office of Vice-Chairman due to forfeiture as defined in <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article XII, Section 1 </cite>of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, the forty-five-day timetable shall commence with Day 1 on the same calendar day as the pertinent conviction in Tribe, state, or federal court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>k.</num>
      <text>Should a vacancy arise in the Office of Vice-Chairman due to dismissal by the Chairman, the forty-five-day timetable shall commence with Day 1 on the calendar day that the Chairman communicates same dismissal from office to the Vice-Chairman following the extension, as delineated in <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, to the Vice-Chairman of the opportunity to respond to written reasons for the dismissal.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>l.</num>
      <text>Any such appointments to the Office of Vice-Chairman shall not be subject to confirmation by the Legislature.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>m.</num>
      <text>Upon any vacancy in the Office of Legislator that arises with less than six months remaining in the applicable term, the Chairman shall nominate, for legislative confirmation, an appointee to same Office within forty-five (45) calendar days who fulfills all salient constitutional requirements to occupy the vacant Office.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>n.</num>
      <text>In accordance with the mandate of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> for legislative confirmation, the Legislature shall vote on any such prospective appointee within five (5) calendar days of receiving a nomination.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>o.</num>
      <text>Should a nominee fail to be approved by the Legislature, the Chairman shall nominate an alternate selection within forty-five (45) calendar days from the vote of the Legislature.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>p.</num>
      <text>The forty-five-day timetable for nomination shall commence with Day 1 on the same calendar day as death or resignation in the event that a vacancy in the Office of Legislator occurs with less than six months remaining in the impacted term.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>q.</num>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>r.</num>
      <text>Should a vacancy in arise in the Office of Legislator with less than six months remaining in the applicable term due to a recall vote conducted by Special Election, the forty-five-day timetable shall commence with Day 1 on the same calendar day as results of the Special Election are formalized as official by the Election Commission in accordance with the provisions of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and Tribe law.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>r.</num>
      <text>Should a vacancy occur in the Office of Legislator with less than six months remaining in the salient term due to forfeiture as defined in <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article XII, Section 1 </cite>of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, the forty-five-day timetable shall commence with Day 1 on the same calendar day as the pertinent conviction in Tribe, state, or federal court.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.5</num>
    <heading>Non-Compliance Contingency</heading>
    <text>Should the Chairman fail to appoint a Vice-Chairman pursuant to the timetables delineated in <cite path="">this statute</cite>, access by the any agents of the Executive Branch to Tribe funds approved for operational costs of same Branch in the annual budget – or in Constitutionally permitted budget modifications – shall terminate on the forty-sixth (46<sup>th</sup>) day of the vacancy. Neither the Executive Branch nor any of its agents shall be able to access Tribe monies appropriated via budget or budget modification for same Branch until a Vice-Chairman is sworn into Office.</text>
    <text>Should the Chairman fail to nominate an appointee for legislative confirmation as provided for in <cite path="">this statute</cite>, then access by any gents of the Executive Branch to Tribe funds appropriate for operational costs of same Branch in the annual budget – or in Constitutionally permitted budget modifications – shall terminate on the forty-sixth (46<sup>th</sup>) day of  the vacancy. Neither the Executive Branch nor any of its agents shall be able to access Tribe monies allocated via budget or budget modification for same Branch until a Constitutionally qualified appointee is nominated to the Legislature for confirmation.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.6</num>
    <heading>Effective Date</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This Act</cite> is effective upon signature of the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe or upon signature of the Speaker of the Kiowa Legislature following legislative override. The forty-five-day timeline for appointments to any vacancies preceding enactment of this law shall commence with any such signature.</text>
  </section>
</document>
