<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-015">
  <num>KL-CY-2025-015</num>
  <heading>2025 Moratorium on Funding for Existing Tribally Owned Corporations</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-08-19</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-08-09</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2025-015.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-015</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe is a sovereign nation and has been so since time immemorial; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Tribe exercises full enjoyment of the inherent powers of government, including self-determination and autonomy over internal affairs encompassing Tribe citizens, lands, and resources; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> on April 17, 2017, qualified voters of the Tribe ratified the Kiowa Constitution as "the supreme law of the land"; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Legislature's duties include monitoring the actions of the government, accessing the needs of the People, and making laws toward better government to address the needs of the People under <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 1 </cite>of the Kiowa Constitution; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Legislature is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(a)</cite> of same Constitution; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Legislature is vested with the authority for budgeting the expenditure of Kiowa money (Art. VI, <cite>Section 6(b)</cite>(ii)); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the budget of the Kiowa Tribe shall include all revenue and funds controlled by the Tribe including government funding, grants, business revenue, gaming revenue, and all revenue and funds received by the Tribe from any and all sources (Art. VI, <cite>Section 6(b)</cite>(iii)); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> every funding item in the annual budget must have been previously authorized by law. No monies shall be drawn from the Treasury except by signature of the Chairman and except upon authorization and appropriation by law (Art. VI, <cite>Section 6(b)</cite>(v)); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature is empowered by same Constitution to promulgate codes and statutes to protect Kiowa Tribal Citizens; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature previously passed into law the Kiowa Tribe Uniform Commercial Business Code of 2023, Resolution No. KL-CY-2023-011, <cite>Article 5</cite>  of which permits the Chairman to create tribal corporations; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> recognizing that all business revenue of the Tribe must be contained in a tribal budget and that no moneys may be spent until and unless authorized and appropriated by law, the legislature is concerned that funds held, managed or controlled in relation to businesses formed by the Chairman pursuant to the Kiowa Tribe Uniform Commercial Business Code of 2023, Resolution No. KL-CY-2023-011 may have been or may be in the future spent without the requisite budget approval, authorization or appropriation by law; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe Legislature does herein establish a moratorium on the withdrawal of any money from the treasury, or the spending or transferring of any money by or for Tribally Owned businesses created pursuant to the Kiowa Tribe Uniform Commercial Business Code of 2023, Resolution No. KL-CY-2023-011.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that no money may be drawn from the Treasury, transferred, moved or spent on or by any of the following: Kiowa, Inc.; Kiowa Technology, Inc.; Kiowa Telecommunications, Inc.; Kiowa Farms, Inc.; Kiowa Ranch, Inc.; Kiowa Tribal Loan Fund, Inc.; or Kiowa Education Foundation, Inc.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> whether or not named or listed herein, no money may be drawn from the treasury, transferred, moved or spent on or by for any new or existing business created pursuant to the Kiowa Tribe Uniform Commercial Business Code of 2023, Resolution No. KL-CY-2023-011.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> the Chairman shall provide, within 30 days, a full and complete list of every business created pursuant to the Kiowa Tribe Uniform Commercial Business Code of 2023, Resolution No. KL-CY-2023-011.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> the Chairman shall provide, within 60 days, a full and complete financial accounting for each and every business created pursuant to the Kiowa Tribe Uniform Commercial Business Code of 2023, Resolution No. KL-CY-2023-011.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> nothing herein shall be construed to apply to the Kiowa Casino Operations Authority (KCOA) which is established pursuant to a specific tribal charter.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>BE IT FINALLY RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that this Resolution shall remain in effect until duly repealed by the Legislature.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution KL-CY-2025-015 was duly voted upon by the Legislature on August 9th, 2025, at a Legislative Regular Session C-(100), with a vote of (7) in favor and (0) opposed, (0) abstaining, and (0) absent, according to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>LEGISLATIVE RESOLUTION – KL-CY-2025-015</strong>
    </text>
    <text><strong>Sponsors:</strong> Michael Primus, District 2.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Co-Sponsors:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2025-015 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the 12th day of August, 2025, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ]	VETO - RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION: _________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________________</text>
    <text>On this ____ day of ________, 2025.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ]	NO</text>
    <text>LEGISLATIVE OVERRIDE ORDER: KLO-CY-2025-0XX</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Legislative Order, KL-CY-2025-00X was duly voted upon by the Legislature on __________________, 2025, at a Legislative Override Order Session with a vote of ______ in favor and _____ opposed, and _____ abstaining, _____Absent.  Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
