<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-007">
  <num>KL-CY-2025-007</num>
  <heading>Resolution to Adopt the K.E.A. Mission Statement, Affirming the Role of Education in Personal Growth and Strengthened Kiowa Identity.</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2025-04-22</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2025-04-12</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2025-007.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2025-007</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Whereas,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Education Agency, established August 13th, 2022, has become a fundamental agency for personal growth and self-discovery, enabling individuals to reach their full potential, and contribute meaningfully to family and community;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Whereas,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa people have a rich cultural heritage that is integral to our identity, and preserving this heritage is essential for the continuation of our traditions, language, and ways of life;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Whereas,</conjunction>
      <text> there is any concern that the pursuit of education may be misconstrued as a departure from our cultural roots or as an adoption of colonial or Western values, we affirm the role of education in concert with personal growth and Kiowa identity;</text>
      <text><strong>Be it resolved</strong>, that education, as pursued by the Kiowa people, is a means to strengthen and enhance our identity, equipping us to preserve and promote our language, culture, and traditions in a rapidly changing world;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Be it further resolved,</conjunction>
      <text> that the sector of our tribal organization that is solely dedicated to the personal growth, learning, and development of the Kiowa people is the Kiowa Education Agency;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Be it further resolved,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Kiowa Education Agency reaffirms its commitment to integrating Kiowa cultural values, language, and teachings into educational efforts, ensuring that learning is a complimentary path to both personal development and cultural preservation;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Be it further resolved,</conjunction>
      <text> that all programmatic functions of the Kiowa Education Agency seek to fulfill the charge and obligation to create spaces for the inclusion of Kiowa cultural values, language, history, art, culture, teachings and contemporary life as a Kiowa-centered and holistic approach;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Be it further resolved,</conjunction>
      <text> that the pursuit of education by Kiowa individuals does not represent an abandonment of our heritage or a succumbing to colonialism but is instead an act of empowerment, allowing us to navigate diverse spaces while remaining grounded in our Kiowa identity;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>Be it further resolved,</conjunction>
      <text> this resolution serves as a declaration that the Kiowa Education Agency views education as a vital component of cultural reclamation and sustainability, language continuance, resilience, and continuous evolution of our people.</text>
      <text>
        <strong>Mission statement of the Kiowa Education Agency</strong>
      </text>
      <text><strong>T</strong>he Kiowa Education Agency, established August 13<sup>th</sup>, 2022, has become a fundamental agency for personal growth and self-discovery, enabling Kiowa citizens to reach their full potential and contribute meaningfully to family and community. The rich cultural heritage of the Kiowa people is integral to our identity, and preserving our heritage is essential for the continuation of our traditions, language, and ways of life. One of our guiding principles is that the pursuit of education should not be misconstrued as a departure from our cultural roots or as an adoption of colonial or Western values. Our collective goals affirm the role of education in concert with personal growth and Kiowa identity. Education, as pursued by the Kiowa people, is a means to strengthen and enhance our identity, equipping us to preserve and promote our language, culture, and traditions in a rapidly changing world. The sector of our tribal organization that is solely dedicated to the personal growth, learning, and development of the Kiowa people is the Kiowa Education Agency. The Kiowa Education Agency reaffirms its commitment to integrating Kiowa cultural values, language, and teachings into educational efforts, ensuring that learning is a complimentary path to both personal development and cultural preservation. A core goal of the Kiowa Education Agency is to create spaces for the inclusion and prominence of Kiowa cultural values, language, history, art, culture, teachings and contemporary life as an act of sovereignty. Through Kiowa-centered and holistic approaches we embrace education an act of empowerment, allowing us to navigate diverse spaces while remaining grounded in our Kiowa identity. For all operations and decisions, education is declared as a vital component of cultural reclamation and sustainability, language continuance, resilience, and the continuous evolution of our Kiowa people.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE IT BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Legislature hereby adopts the K.E.A. Mission Statement, Affirming the Role of Education in Personal Growth and Strengthened Kiowa Identity.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution KL-CY-2025-007, was duly voted upon by the Legislature on April 12, 2025, at a Legislative Regular Session XCVI-(96) with a vote of (6) in favor and (0) opposed, (0) abstaining, and (1) absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>LEGISLATURE - RESOLUTION NO. KL-CY-2025-007:</text>
    <text>SPONSOR: Warren Queton, District 7</text>
    <text>CO-SPONSOR(S):</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2025-007 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the 17<sup>th</sup>  day of April, 2025, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by the Constitution.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>______________________________</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text class="center">Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ]	VETO - RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ]	NO</text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution KL-CY-2025-0XX was overridden with Order KLO-CY-2025-0XX and duly voted upon by the Legislature on __________________, 2028, at a Legislative Order Session with a vote of ______ in favor and ______opposed, and _____ abstaining, _____Absent.  Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
