<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2023-001">
  <num>KL-CY-2023-001</num>
  <heading>Kiowa Housing Law</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2023-01-19</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2023-01-14</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2023-001.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2023-001</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>At a duly called Session of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe, held this 14th day of January, 2023, the following Resolution and Law was adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature is vested with authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6 (a) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe Legislature determined it is in the best interest of the Kiowa Tribe to amend the Kiowa Tribe Housing Authority Law of 2019 to "Kiowa Housing Law" (see attachment), to bring into compliance with the Kiowa Tribe Constitution and laws of the Tribe for the benefit of Tribal Members and delivery of housing services, and;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Kiowa Tribe Legislature hereby enacts the attached law entitled, "Kiowa Housing Law".</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution KL-CY-2023-001, was duly voted upon by the Kiowa Tribe Legislature at a duly called Regular Session LXIX, January 14, 2023, with a vote of (6)-yes and (0)-no, (0)-abstaining, and (1)-absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Anita Johnson</text>
    <text>Secretary of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>LEGISLATURE-RESOLUTION NO. KL-CY-2023-001:</strong>
    </text>
    <text><strong>SPONSOR: </strong>Anita Johnson, Secretary/District #5</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CO-SPONSOR(S):</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District #1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>X</p>
              <p>Out of District</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District #2</p>
            </td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District #3</p>
            </td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Alana Quetone</p>
              <p>District #4</p>
            </td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Anita Johnson</p>
              <p>District #5</p>
            </td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District #6</p>
            </td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District #7</p>
            </td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2023-001 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the ______ day of January, 2023, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>.</text>
    <text>Anita Johnson</text>
    <text>Secretary of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[ X ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ] 	VETO	-	RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this <u>19</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>January</u>, 2023.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird,</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the __________ day of _______________, 2023.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ] 	NO</text>
    <text>
      <strong>LEGISLATIVE OVERRIDE ORDER: KLO-CY-2023-0XX</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District #1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District #2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District #3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Alana Quetone</p>
              <p>District #4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Anita Johnson</p>
              <p>District #5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District #6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District #7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Legislative Order, KL-CY-2023-XXX was duly voted upon by the Legislature on ____________________ 2023, at a Legislative Override Order Session with a vote of _________ in favor and ________ opposed, and _________ abstaining, _________ Absent. Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Anita Onco-Johnson</text>
    <text>Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <text class="center">
    <strong>Kiowa Housing Law</strong>
  </text>
  <section>
    <num>1</num>
    <heading>CITIATION.</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This Statute</cite> shall be called the Kiowa Housing Law.</text>
    <text>Notice to Legislative History: The first tribal legislation concerning the Kiowa Tribe Housing Authority is the KIOWA TRIBE HOUSING AUTHORITY REFORM ACT OF 2017, which authorized the Kiowa Tribe to reform the Tribe's Housing Authority to bring it into compliance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and laws of the Tribe, to take full responsibility to assert the Tribe's sovereign authority to address the housing needs of Members of the Tribe, and to abolish the outdated method of subjecting the Tribe's Housing sovereign status to the full or partial control of the State of Oklahoma by operating the Tribe's Housing Authority, in whole or in part, as a State Agency and to assume total assets of the Kiowa Housing Authority. The second piece of tribal legislation on the issue is the Kiowa Tribe Housing Authority Act of 2019. This amendment is made in 2022 to fix certain errors and inaccuracies as noted below. Two versions of this Law are provided. First is one showing the changes, where additions are underlined. The second version is merely clean, where all changes are accepted and it is the clean version which is the official Kiowa Housing Law.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>2</num>
    <heading>HOUSING AUTHORITY CREATED</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(A)</num>
      <text>Pursuant to the Kiowa Tribe Constitution, <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Sections 1 </cite>and 6, the Kiowa Legislature shall have the power to make laws toward a better government to address the needs of the people, to create commissions, and to establish executive boards. The Legislature therefore created the Kiowa Tribe Housing Authority (hereinafter referred to as the Authority) which is an agency of the Kiowa Tribe having the purposes, powers, and duties as herein or hereafter by law. The Legislature also created the Kiowa Housing Commission as a Constitutional Commission to direct the affairs of the Authority.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(B)</num>
      <text>In any suit, action or proceeding involving the validity or enforcement of or relating to any of its contracts, the Authority shall be conclusively deemed to have become established and authorized to transact business and exercise its powers upon proof of the adoption of this ordinance. A copy of the ordinance duly certified by the Secretary of the Legislature of Kiowa Tribe shall be admissible in evidence in any suit, action or proceeding. The Tribal Courts shall take judicial notice of <cite path="">this Act</cite>.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(C)</num>
      <text>All housing goals shall be documented in the IHP current Kiowa Housing Law, which describes the Authority as the Kiowa Tribally designated Housing Entity (TDHE) and the Recipient as required by the Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
</document>
