<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001">
  <num>KL-CY-2024-001</num>
  <heading>Establishment for Recognition of Judicial Proceedings in Foreign Courts-Full Faith and Credit Act of 2024</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-01-23</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-01-13</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2024-001.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe of Oklahoma is a federally recognized Indian Tribe with a Constitution approved by the Secretary of the Interior; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature, is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6 (a) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature, is authorized under the Kiowa Constitution and is empowered to promulgate and enforce codes and laws, to protect Kiowa Tribal Citizens; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature, finds it necessary, to enact resolution "Establishment for Recognition of Judicial Proceedings in Foreign Courts-Full Faith and Credit Act of 2024"; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Official Seals of the Courts of the Kiowa Tribe and the court of original jurisdiction for the Kiowa Tribe, is the Trial Court. The court of appellate jurisdiction for the Kiowa Tribe, is the Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> to ensure the authenticity of official documents of said courts, the Court Clerks, for each court shall ensure, that the official seal for each court clearly state "Trial Court of the Kiowa Tribe" and "Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe", respectively.</text>
      <text><strong>THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</strong> the Kiowa Tribe Legislature, having been delegated certain authorities under the Kiowa Constitution, the governing body of the Kiowa Tribe, does hereby enact "Establishment of Recognition of Judicial Proceedings in Foreign Courts – Full Faith and Credit Act of 2024".</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution KL-CY-2024-001 was duly voted upon by the Legislature on January 13, 2024, at a Legislative Regular Session LXXXI-(81), with a vote of (6) in favor and (0) opposed, 0() abstaining, and (1) absent, according to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Anita Johnson</text>
    <text>Secretary of the Legislature</text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>LEGISLATIVE RESOLUTION - KL-CY-2024-001</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>
        <u>Sponsor: Michael Primus, District 2 Legislator</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>
        <u>Co-Sponsor: Anita Johnson, District 5 Legislator</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District #1</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District #2</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District #3</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Alana Quetone</p>
              <p>District #4</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Anita Johnson</p>
              <p>District #5</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District #6</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District #7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>X</p>
              <p>Present-out of district</p>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2024-001 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the 26th day of January, 2024, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>.</text>
    <text>Anita Johnson</text>
    <text>Secretary of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[   ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[   ] 	VETO – RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this <u>24</u><sup><u>th</u></sup> day of <u>January</u>, 2024.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the _____ day of _________________, 2024.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[   ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[   ] 	NO</text>
    <text>
      <strong>LEGISLATIVE OVERRIDE ORDER: KLO-CY-2024-0XX</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District #1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District #2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District #3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Alana Quetone</p>
              <p>District #4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Anita Johnson</p>
              <p>District #5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District #6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District #7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Legislative Order, KL-CY-2024-00X was duly voted upon by the Legislature on ____________________, 2024, at a Legislative Override Order Session with a vote of _______ in favor and _______ opposed, and _______ abstaining, _______ Absent. Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Anita Johnson</text>
    <text>Secretary of the Legislature</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <section>
    <num>1.1</num>
    <heading>Short Title</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This enactment</cite> shall be known as the "Establishment for Recognition of Judicial Proceedings in Foreign Courts-Full Faith and Credit".</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.2</num>
    <heading>Official Seals of the Courts of the Kiowa Tribe</heading>
    <text>The court of original jurisdiction for the Kiowa Tribe is the Trial Court of the Kiowa Tribe. The court of appellate jurisdiction for the Kiowa Tribe is the Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe. To ensure the authenticity of official documents of said courts, the Court Clerks for each court shall ensure that the official seals for each court clearly state "Trial Court of the Kiowa Tribe" and "Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe" respectively.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.3</num>
    <heading>Definitions and Recitals</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>"Domestic Foreign Court" means any court or constitutionally established tribunal of the United States of America, any state, commonwealth, or territory of the United States of America, or any federally recognized Indian nation, tribe, pueblo, band, or Alaska Native village, duly established under federal law or tribal law, including Courts of Indian Offenses organized pursuant to Title 25, Part 11 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>"Judicial Officer" means any judge, justice, magistrate or other officer duly seated and authorized under federal, state, or tribal law to resolve disputes and enter judgments in a Domestic Foreign Court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>"Domestic Foreign Judgment" means any final written judgment, decree or order of a trial court duly signed by a judicial officer and filed in a Domestic Foreign Court.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.4</num>
    <heading>Recognition of Domestic Foreign Judgements-Full Faith and Credit</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>The Trial Court of the Kiowa Tribe shall grant full faith and credit and cause to be enforced any Domestic Foreign Judgment where the Domestic Foreign Court that issued the judgment grants reciprocity to judgments of the courts of the Kiowa Tribe, provided, a Domestic Foreign Judgment shall receive no greater effect or full faith and credit under <cite path="1.4">this rule</cite> than would a similar or comparable judgment of any other Domestic Foreign Court.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>To the extent that a Domestic Foreign Court requires the Kiowa Tribe to grant reciprocity to judgments from the Domestic Foreign Court before granting reciprocity in return, the Trial Court Clerk is authorized to provide any documentation, whether in the form of a copy of this ordinance or in a certification from the court clerk's office, to the Domestic Foreign Court to secure said grant of reciprocity.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.5</num>
    <heading>Listing of Domestic Foreign Courts Granting Reciprocity</heading>
    <text>A list of the Domestic Foreign Courts that grant full faith and credit to the courts of the Kiowa Tribe shall be maintained by the Trial Court Clerk. Any Domestic Foreign Court may provide the Trial Court Clerk a copy of the ordinance, statute, court rule or other evidence that demonstrates that the Domestic Foreign Court grants reciprocity to the courts of the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.6</num>
    <heading>Filing of Domestic Foreign Judgements</heading>
    <text>A copy of any Domestic Foreign Judgment authenticated in accordance with the applicable act of Congress or of the statutes of this state or the law of the tribe may be filed in the office of the Trial Court Clerk of Kiowa Tribe. The Trial Court Clerk shall treat the Domestic Foreign Judgment in the same manner as a judgment of the Trial Court the Kiowa Tribe which may be enforced or satisfied in like manner.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.7</num>
    <heading>Notice of Filing</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(1)</num>
      <text>At the time of the filing of the Domestic Foreign Judgment with the Trial Court Clerk, the party filing the judgment or that party's attorney shall make and file with the Trial Court Clerk an affidavit setting forth the name and last-known address of all parties in the action, including the name and last-known address of any party's attorney.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(2)</num>
      <text>Promptly upon the filing of the Domestic Foreign Judgment and the affidavit, the Trial Court Clerk shall mail notice of the filing of the Domestic Foreign Judgment to the party against whom the judgment was rendered at the address given and shall make a note of the mailing in the docket. The notice shall include the name and address of the party filing the judgment, and that party's attorney, if any. In addition, the party filing the judgment shall mail a notice of the filing of the judgment to the party against whom judgment was rendered and shall file an affidavit proving the mailing of the notice with the Trial Court Clerk within ten (10) days of the date that the Domestic Foreign Judgment was filed with the Trial Court Clerk. Failure of the Trial Court Clerk to mail the notice of filing of the judgment shall not affect the enforcement proceedings if an affidavit proving the mailing of the notice has been filed by the party filing the judgment.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(3)</num>
      <text>No execution or other process for enforcement of a Domestic Foreign Judgment filed hereunder shall issue until the affidavit proving the mailing of the notice has been filed with the Trial Court Clerk, and twenty (20) days have expired from the date the judgment was filed in the Trial Court.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.8</num>
    <heading>Approval and Enactment</heading>
    <text>The Legislature hereby approves and Enacts the "Establishment for Recognition of Judicial Proceedings in Foreign Courts-Full Faith and Credit Act of 2024".</text>
  </section>
</document>
