<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-021">
  <num>KL-CY-2024-021</num>
  <heading>Amended Resolution of the Kiowa Tribe Legislature Authorizing Bank of Oklahoma Bank Accounts, Signers, Powers Granted and Limitations</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2024-12-24</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2024-12-14</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2024-021.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-021</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Kiowa Tribe (the "Tribe") is organized under a constitution, duly adopted and approved by the voters of the Tribe on April 17, 2017 and approved by the U.S. Secretary of the Interior ("Secretary")(the "Constitution"); and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(a) of the Constitution</cite>, the Legislature is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions, including the power to authorize the Chairman to enter into contracts for financial and banking services; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Tribe has a need to invest and secure its financial resources; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Tribe has determined that entering into a contract with Bank of Oklahoma and establishing a banking relationship with Bank of Oklahoma is in the Kiowa Tribe's best financial interest; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text> the Bank of Oklahoma has requested the Tribe to determine who is officially authorized to act as Agents for the Tribe and to exercise certain powers as indicated below;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text> that the Legislature hereby authorizes the following persons and positions to be designated agents of the Tribe in all transactions with Bank of Oklahoma:</text>
      <text>Name and Title or Position				Signature</text>
      <text>
        <u>Kiowa Tribal Chairman</u>
      </text>
      <text>Lawrence SpotteBird</text>
      <text>
        <u>Tribe's Chief Financial Officer</u>
      </text>
      <text>William Weaver</text>
      <text>
        <u>Deputy Chief Financial Officer</u>
      </text>
      <text>Summer Palmer</text>
      <text>
        <u>General Ledger Accountant</u>
      </text>
      <text>Violet Kay Langley</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE</conjunction>
      <text> BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED, the following powers are granted to the persons named above by listing the letter corresponding to their name above before each power.  Following each power, it is indicated the number of Agent signatures required to exercise the power:</text>
      <text><u>A, B, C</u>	1) Open a deposit or share account(s) in the name of the Tribe.	<u>2</u></text>
      <text>(IF C exercises this power, either A or B must sign)</text>
      <text><u>A, B, C, D, </u>	2) Endorse checks and orders for the payment of money or 		<u>2</u></text>
      <text>Otherwise withdraw or transfer funds on deposit with this</text>
      <text>Financial Institution.										    (If C, D or E exercises this power, either A or B must sign)</text>
      <text><u>A, B</u>		3)  Borrow money on behalf of and in the name of the Tribe, 	<u>2</u></text>
      <text>sign, execute and deliver promissory notes or other evidences</text>
      <text>of indebtedness.  This power requires prior authorization from</text>
      <text>the Legislature.  This resolution signifies prior authorization for</text>
      <text>a P-Card or Credit Card to be obtained by the signatories above.</text>
      <text><u>A, B, C, D</u>	4)  Endorse, assign, transfer, mortgage or pledge bills receivable,	<u>2</u></text>
      <text>warehouse receipts, bills of lading, stocks, bonds, real estate</text>
      <text>or other property now owned or hereafter owned or acquired</text>
      <text>by the Tribe as security for sums borrowed, and to discount</text>
      <text>the same, unconditionally guarantee payment of all bills</text>
      <text>received, negotiated or discounted, and to waive demand,</text>
      <text>presentment, protest, notice of protest and notice of non-</text>
      <text>payment.</text>
      <text><u>A, B, C, D</u>	5)  Enter into a written lease for the purpose of renting, 		<u>2</u></text>
      <text>maintaining, accessing and terminating a Safe Deposit</text>
      <text>box with Bank of Oklahoma.</text>
      <text><u>C, D</u>		6)  Authorize certain financial staff to have limited "authority	<u>2</u></text>
      <text>and powers, including Inquiry Only Authorization."</text>
      <text>(If D exercises this power in the absence of C, either A or B</text>
      <text>must sign)</text>
      <text><strong>FINALLY, BE IT RESOLVED, </strong>the Legislature declares:</text>
      <text>Bank of Oklahoma is designated as a depository for the funds of the Kiowa Tribe and is to provide other financial accommodations as indicated by this Resolution;</text>
      <text>This Resolution shall continue to be in full force and effect until express written notice of its recission or modification has been received and recorded by Bank of Oklahoma.  Any revocation, modification or replacement of this resolution received by Bank of Oklahoma must be accompanied by a Legislature Resolution;</text>
      <text>The signature of an Agent on this resolution is conclusive evidence of their authority to act on behalf of the Kiowa Tribe.  Any Agent, so long as they act in a representative capacity as an Agent of the Tribe, is authorized to make any and all other contracts, agreements, stipulations and orders which they may deem advisable for the effective exercise of powers as indicated on Page 2, from time to time with the Bank of Oklahoma, subject to any restrictions of this resolution or otherwise agree to in writing;</text>
      <text>All transactions, if any, with respect to any deposits, withdrawals, rediscounts, and borrowings by or on behalf of the Tribe with the Bank of Oklahoma prior to the adoption of this resolution are hereby ratified, approved and confirmed.</text>
      <text>The Tribe agrees to the terms and conditions of any account agreement, properly opened by any Agent of the Tribe. The Tribe authorizes the Bank of Oklahoma, at any time, to charge the Tribe for all checks, drafts, or other orders, for the payment of money, that are drawn on the Bank of Oklahoma, so long as they contain the required number of signatures for this purpose.</text>
      <text>The Tribe acknowledges and agrees that the Bank of Oklahoma may furnish at its discretion automated access devices to Agents of the Tribe to facilitate those powers authorized by this resolution or other resolutions in effect at the time of issuance. The term "automated access device" includes, but is not limited to, purchase cards (aka "P-cards), credit cards, automated teller machines (ATM), and debit cards.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Amended Resolution KL-CY-2024-021 was duly voted upon by the Legislature on December 14, 2024, at Legislative Regular Session XCII-(92), with a vote of (6) in favor and (0) opposed, (0) abstaining, and (1) absent, according to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>AMENDED LEGISLATIVE RESOLUTION –KL-CY-2024-021</strong>
    </text>
    <text><strong>Sponsors:</strong> Michael Primus, District 2.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Co-Sponsors:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>YES</p>
              <p>Hàu</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>NO</p>
              <p>Hàu:né</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSTAIN</p>
              <p>Háun á</p>
            </th>
            <th proof="needed">
              <p>ABSENT</p>
              <p>Héñgyádàu</p>
            </th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td>X</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td>X</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Amended Resolution No. KL-CY-2024-021 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on January 15, 2025, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ]	VETO - RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>Lawrence Spottedbird</text>
    <text>Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe</text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the ____ day of _________, 2025.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ]	NO</text>
    <text>LEGISLATIVE OVERRIDE ORDER: KLO-CY-2025-0XX</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Kyle Ataddlety</p>
              <p>District 1</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Michael Primus</p>
              <p>District 2</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Timothy Satepauhoodle</p>
              <p>District 3</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Cole DeLaune</p>
              <p>District 4</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Tiya Rosario</p>
              <p>District 5</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Ben Wolf</p>
              <p>District 6</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p>Warren Queton</p>
              <p>District 7</p>
            </td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Legislative Order, KL-CY-2025-00X was duly voted upon by the Legislature on __________________, 2025, at a Legislative Override Order Session with a vote of ______ in favor and _____ opposed, and _____ abstaining, _____Absent.  Pursuant to the authority vested in the Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>Michael Primus</text>
    <text>Speaker of the Legislature</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
