<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Kiowa Code of Law">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>5</num>
  <heading>Court</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.01</num>
    <heading>Courts and Appointment of Judges and Justices</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.01.010</num>
      <heading>JUDICIAL POWER</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>JUDICIAL POWER.</heading>
        <text>The judicial power of the Kiowa Tribe shall be vested in one Supreme Court and one Trial Court. The Legislature may also establish inferior courts, as needed, by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>JUDICIAL COMMISSION.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>There shall be a Judicial Commission comprised of five Members of the Tribe nominated by the Chairman subject to confirmation by the Legislature in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the constitutional</cite> requirements outlined in Art. VIII Sec. 9 (a) of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>. No person who has been convicted of a felony may serve as a Judicial Commission Member. Judicial Commission members shall serve four (4) year staggered terms.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Judicial Commission shall adopt a Code of Ethics for the Judges and Justices, based on the Model Code of Judicial Conduct. The Judicial Commission shall adopt a Code of Ethics for attorneys and lay advocates, based on the Model Rules of Professional Conduct. The Judicial Commission shall hear any complaints regarding Justices, Judges, attorneys and lay advocates. The Judicial Commission shall have the power to make recommendations to the Chief Justice and Chief Judge to discipline a Justice, Judge, or Pro-Tem Judge. The Judicial Commission shall have the power to make recommendations to the Chief Justice or Chief Judge to discipline or remove a Court clerk or other court staff. The Judicial Commission shall have the power to make recommendations to the Legislature to remove a Judge or Justice. The Judicial Commission shall provide each person subject to discipline or removal with due process.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Judicial Commission shall have the power to regulate the conduct of lawyers and lay advocates licensed to practice in the Courts. A denial or revocation of a license to practice in the Courts issued by the Chief Judge may be appealed to the Judicial Commission, provided that any decision by the Judicial Commission regarding such license may be appealed to the Chief Justice, who shall make a final decision in writing.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|I|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.01.020</num>
      <heading>SUPREME COURT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>HOW CONSTITUTED.</heading>
        <text>The Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe shall consist of one Chief Justice and four Associate Justices. The selection of each Judge and Justice shall be upon nomination by the Chairman, subject to confirmation by the legislature as outlined in Art. VIII Sec. 2 of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>. The terms of each Judge and Justice are further set in Art. VIII Sec. 3 (a) and (b) of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>. The Judicial Commission shall conduct a written evaluation and report of each Justice after one year of service and at such other times as the Judicial Commission deems necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>QUALIFICATIONS.</heading>
        <text>Any individual who is a graduate of an accredited school of law and who is over the age of thirty (30) years, has never been convicted of a felony, and who meets any other requirements contained in <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, shall be eligible to be appointed a justice of the Supreme Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>CHIEF JUSTICE.</heading>
        <text>The Chief Justice or his designee shall preside at all proceedings. The Chief Justice shall hold such position until the expiration of his appointment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>JURISDICTION.</heading>
        <text>The Supreme Court shall have appellate jurisdiction over any case on appeal from the Trial Court. The Supreme Court shall have original and exclusive jurisdiction over any final determination by the Election Commission on a protest or challenge of the results of an election, and such jurisdiction shall include the power to make findings of fact and conclusion of law, and to issue all remedies in law and equity. The Trial Court and the Supreme Court shall not have jurisdiction over traditional religious matters such as the conduct of ceremonies or the possession of sacred objects.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>ORDERS AND REMEDIES.</heading>
        <text>The Supreme Court has the power to issue all remedies in law or in equity necessary and proper to the complete exercise of its jurisdiction; to prevent or remedy any act of the Trial Court beyond the Trial Court's jurisdiction; to cause a Trial Court to act where the Trial Court unlawfully fails or refuses to act within its jurisdiction; and to interpret the Kiowa Constitution and all Kiowa statutes. The Supreme Court shall have the power to invalidate the laws of the Tribe if such laws are in conflict with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>. Decisions of the Supreme Court shall be final. All orders, opinions and decisions of the Supreme Court shall be written and published.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>SALARIES.</heading>
        <text>Justices shall receive reasonable compensation as established by law. No increase or decrease in compensation for Justices shall take effect until after the next General Election except for generally applicable cost of living increases.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>CERTIFIED QUESTIONS OF KIOWA LAW.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Supreme Court has jurisdiction to answer questions of Kiowa Law, including Kiowa constitutional law, certified from any tribal, federal, or state court or from any tribal, federal or state administrative agency.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Supreme Court has jurisdiction to answer questions of Kiowa constitutional law, certified to it by the Legislature, and shall expedite consideration of any certified questions of law. In the exercise of sound discretion, the Kiowa Supreme Court may decline to answer questions certified to it.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Supreme Court may issue rules or administrative orders appropriate to the processing of certified questions.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>APPELLATE PROCEDURE.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>There shall be no right to a trial de novo (new trial) on appeal from the Trial Court to the Supreme Court. The decision of the Supreme Court shall be made on the basis of the file and record of the proceedings in the Trial Court, in addition to the briefs and verbatim memoranda submitted by the parties to the appeal. Oral argument may be allowed, if requested.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Upon the stipulation (agreement) of all parties to an appeal, the decision of the Supreme Court may be made upon the basis of stipulated (agreed upon) facts and/or issues of law and without, or with less than all of, the file and/or verbatim record of the Trial Court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|I|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.01.030</num>
      <heading>TRIAL COURT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>ESTABLISHMENT.</heading>
        <text>A trial Court is hereby established for the Kiowa Tribe and shall be known as the Trial Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>COMPOSITION.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court shall consist of one Chief Judge, one Senior Associate Judge, and other associate judges as deemed necessary by the Legislature by law. The Judicial Commission may conduct a written evaluation and report of each Trial Court Judge after one year of service and at such other times as the Judicial Commission deems necessary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>QUALIFICATIONS OF CHIEF JUDGE AND SENIOR ASSOCIATE JUDGE.</heading>
        <text>Any person admitted to practice before the Supreme Court of the United States, or any United States Circuit Court of Appeals, or the Supreme Court of any state of the United States who is over the age of thirty (30) years, who has never been convicted of a felony, and any other requirements contained in <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, shall be eligible to be appointed Chief Judge or Senior Associate Judge of the Trial Court. No person shall be appointed or serve as a Trial or a Chief Judge who has been found guilty of any crime involving fraud or dishonesty.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>ASSOCIATE TRIAL JUDGES.</heading>
        <text>Any member of the Kiowa Tribe over the age of 25 years who has never been convicted of a felony or a misdemeanor involving fraud or dishonesty, shall be eligible to be appointed associate judge of the Trial Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>SALARIES.</heading>
        <text>Judges shall receive reasonable compensation as established by law. No increase or decrease in salary shall be allowed during the Judge's term, except for cost of living increases that apply to all employees.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>DISQUALIFICATION.</heading>
        <text>No judge shall hear or determine any case at the trial level or appeal when he has a direct interest in the outcome of the case or is related to one of the litigants in the trial, in accordance with the Model Code of Judicial Conduct Rule 2.11(A), or applicable rules adopted by the Judicial Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>REMOVAL.</heading>
        <text>Justices and judges may be removed for cause by the Legislature, but only as set in the removal process contained in Art. VIII, Sec. 9 (b) of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>. Written charges must be delivered to the justice or judge sought to be removed not less than twenty (20) days before the hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>EXISTING TERMS OF OFFICE.</heading>
        <text>Upon the adoption of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, the Judges currently serving shall remain in office with the full judicial authority to act, in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, and pursuant to their employment or contractual terms.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|I|3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.01.040</num>
      <heading>JURISDICTION OF TRIAL COURT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>CRIMINAL JURISDICTION.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court has original jurisdiction over all offenses committed in violation of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, the Kiowa Sex Offender Registration Code (SORNA), and any ordinances or laws of the Tribe when committed by an Indian, within any lands held in trust for, or owned by the Tribe, or held by the United States for the benefit of the Tribe or the people, including any rights of way existing now or in the future (the "Territory").</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>EXCLUSION OF NON-INDIANS.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court has original jurisdiction to enforce the provisions of any Code, ordinance or law of the Kiowa Tribe providing for the exclusion of non-Indians from the Kiowa Territory.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>JUVENILE MATTERS.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court sits as the Juvenile Court and exercises the jurisdiction over such matters.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>CIVIL JURISDICTION.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court has original jurisdiction over all civil actions or controversies, whether at law or equity, arising under <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, laws, customs, and traditions of the Tribe, including cases in which the Tribe or its officials and employees shall be a party. All civil causes of action arising within the Jurisdiction of the Tribe shall be brought in the Trial Court before they can be litigated in any other court. The Trial Court shall also have original jurisdiction over civil regulatory actions involving the registration of convicted sex offenders, as defined in The Kiowa Sex Offender Registration Code (SORNA).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|I|4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.01.050</num>
      <heading>POWERS &amp; DUTIES OF TRIAL COURT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>POWERS.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court has the following powers:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To preserve and enforce order in its immediate presence. (b) To enforce order in the proceedings before it, or before a person empowered to conduct a judicial investigation under its authority.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>To provide for the orderly conduct of proceedings before it or its officers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>To compel obedience to its judgments, orders, and process.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>To supervise and control the conduct of its ministerial officers. (f) To compel the attendance of persons to testify in any hearing or trial.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>To administer oaths in all proceedings held in its courtroom, and in all other cases where it may be necessary in the exercise of its powers and duties.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>To interpret the Kiowa Constitution and laws of the Tribe, and to invalidate laws in conflict with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>To issue all remedies in law and in equity.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>To administer funds received by the Court as a result of fines or sanctions issued by the Court.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>DUTIES.</heading>
        <text>It is the duty of the Courts to hear and decide all cases before it in a fair and impartial manner to the end that justice may be administered, and law and order maintained.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>RULES OF COURT.</heading>
        <text>The time and place of Court sessions of both the Trial and Appellate Courts and all other details of judicial procedure not prescribed in <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite> shall be established by the Chief Justice or Chief Judge of each Court respectively, subject to the authority of the Judicial Commission and/or Legislature to modify such rules.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>PRECEDENTIAL AUTHORITY FOR THE COURTS.</heading>
        <text>The Courts, in deciding matters of both substance and procedure, shall look to, and give weight as precedent to, the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Kiowa Constitution.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Codes, ordinances, Resolutions, and laws enacted by the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Laws passed by the Legislature.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Common law of the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Laws, rules and regulations and cases of the Federal Government, which the Judge or Justice may use as guidance. This provision shall not, however, be deemed to be an adoption of such laws or rules as the law of the Kiowa Tribe nor as a grant or cession of any right, power or authority by the Kiowa Tribe to the Federal Government.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>The laws and rules, and cases interpreting such laws and rules, of the State of Oklahoma. This provision shall not be deemed to be an adoption of such laws or rules as the law of the Kiowa Tribe nor as a grant or cession of any right, power or authority by the Kiowa Tribe to the State of Oklahoma.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>RULES OF CRIMINAL PROCEDURE.</heading>
        <text>The Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure shall govern all criminal proceedings before the Trial Court unless otherwise directed by the laws of the Tribe. In the event that there is a conflict between the Federal Rules and procedures established under Kiowa law, the procedures established in Kiowa law shall control.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>RULES OF EVIDENCE.</heading>
        <text>The Federal Rules of Evidence shall constitute the rules of evidence, to the extent that they do not conflict with Kiowa law and tradition, in all proceedings before the Trial Courts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>COURTS OF RECORD.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Trial and Appellate Courts are hereby declared to be Courts of Record and the Clerk thereof shall certify under seal as to the accuracy and validity of the files and records of all proceedings before the Courts of the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Clerk of the Courts shall take, preserve and certify under seal to the accuracy of a verbatim record of the proceedings before the Courts. Such record may be taken and recorded by a stenographic, electronic, mechanical, or other recording means of devices approved by the Chief Judge of the Court as a trustworthy means of creating a permanent verbatim record of all proceedings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Chief Judge of the Trial Court and Chief Justice of the Supreme Court shall, by rule, prescribe the length of time such verbatim transcripts shall be preserved by the Clerk.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>It shall be a criminal offense, punishable by the penalties and under the rules and procedures of Kiowa law for the Clerk of the Trial Courts to knowingly make or keep a false file, record or certificate or to alter, amend or destroy any file, record or transcript without lawful authority.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>VICTIM'S RIGHTS.</heading>
        <text>The Kiowa Tribe recognizes that victims of crime, including victims of Domestic Violence and Elderly Abuse, must be treated with the utmost respect in all criminal investigations and court proceedings. In addition to the rights enumerated in Rule 60 of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure, victims shall have the following rights:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>To be treated with fairness and respect for the victim's dignity and privacy throughout the criminal justice process.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>To be reasonably protected from the defendant, or anyone acting on his or her behalf, from intimidation, threat, harassment or abuse.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>To confer with the Tribal Prosecutor regarding the disposition of the case.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>To refuse a personal interview by the defense attorney or anyone representing the defendant regarding the charges alleged in the criminal complaint.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>To be accompanied by a victim's advocate, family member or friend, at all court proceedings.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>To be compensated for all reasonable economic losses sustained by the victim caused by the defendant's criminal conduct.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>To have personal property seized as evidence returned promptly.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>To be informed, upon request, when the defendant is released from custody or has escaped.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|I|5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.01.060</num>
      <heading>OFFICERS OF THE COURT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>OFFICERS.</heading>
        <text>Officers of the Trial Court include:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Prosecutor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A Court Appointed Counsel or Public Defender.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Clerk of the Court and any deputies, probation officers, referees, or masters.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>All law enforcement officers, including all regularly employed police officers of the Kiowa Tribe, special officers, police officers, conservation officers, and federal officers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>All Attorneys and lay advocates who are members of the Bar of the Kiowa Tribe or otherwise admitted to practice before the Courts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>AUTHORITY OF PROSECUTOR APPOINTED BY TRIBE.</heading>
        <text>In any and all criminal proceedings in any and all Courts, the Chairman shall appoint a person to act as prosecutor who shall have power and authority to sign, file, and present any and all complaints, subpoenas, affidavits, motions, processes, and papers of any kind and to appear before all Courts, Commissions, or Tribunals in criminal proceedings; provided, that if the Chairman fails to appoint a prosecutor within sixty (60) days of the effective date of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, then the Judicial Commission, or any member of the Judicial Commission, shall select a prosecutor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>PUBLIC DEFENDER.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Kiowa Tribe hereby establishes the Office of Public Defender. The Chairman shall appoint a suitable person to serve as the Public Defender, subject to an appropriation of funds for such purposes in an approved budget.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Any person who is admitted to practice law before any State Supreme Court or U.S. District Court, and is in good standing, shall be qualified for the office.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Public Defender shall be compensated upon a contractual basis, in accordance with the Kiowa Tribe's hiring and/or contracting requirements.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The Public Defender shall perform the following duties:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Upon order of the court, defend, advise, and counsel without expense to the defendant, any person who is not financially able to employ counsel in the following proceedings and circumstances:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Offenses triable in the Trial Court at all stages of the proceedings, including the preliminary examination, but only for those offenses defined under <cite path="|13.04.010">Section 13.04.010</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Extradition hearings.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>Sanity hearings only when appointed by the court.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Involuntary commitment hearings only when appointed by the court.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>Juvenile delinquency hearings only when appointed by the court.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(vi)</num>
              <text>Appeals to the Court of Appeals.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Keep a record of all services rendered by the public defender in that capacity and file with the Legislature an annual report of those services.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>By December 1 of each year, file with the Chief Judge and Legislature an annual report on the average cost of defending a major offense. For the purpose of <cite path="|5.01.060|(c)">Section 5.01.060(c)</cite>, a major offense shall mean an offense, serious offense or dangerous offense as defined in <cite path="|13.04.010">Section 13.04.010</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>The Public Defender may, with the consent and at salaries authorized by law, appoint those full-time and part-time deputies and assistants necessary to conduct the affairs of the office. The appointments shall be in accordance with the Kiowa Tribe's hiring and/or contracting requirements.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(E)</num>
            <text>The Public Defender shall petition the court to withdraw as attorney of record and the court may grant such petition, whenever private counsel is employed either by the defendant or by any other person to represent such defendant and such private counsel is accepted by the defendant.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>APPEARANCE OF ATTORNEYS.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Attorneys, if qualified, may appear before the Courts in all cases.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Qualification of Attorneys. Attorneys may become a member of the Bar of the Courts, if they are admitted to practice before the Supreme Court of the United States, a United States Circuit Court of Appeals, U.S. District Court, or the Supreme Court of any state, and are in good standing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Certification. Any attorney eligible under <cite path="|5.01.060|(d)|(2)">Section 5.01.060(d)(2)</cite>, who desires to practice in the Courts shall obtain a certificate from the Court authorizing his or her practice before the Courts each calendar year. A certificate must be obtained prior to any appearance by the attorney in Court. The annual fee shall be established by the Chief Judge at not less than $100.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Dignity &amp; Ethics. Any applicant for a certificate to become a member of the Bar of the Kiowa Courts shall agree that he or she will conform to the standards of conduct established by the Professionalism Committee in the performance of his duties as an attorney before the Courts.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Contempt. In the event that an attorney is found guilty of contempt before any Court or contempt outside the presence of any Court, the judge may levy a penalty for the contempt not to exceed the sum of Five hundred Dollars ($500.00), and if any attorney who fails to pay the fine as provided by any judgment of any Court therefore, he shall be disqualified to practice before the Courts.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Attorney's fees. Attorneys practicing before the Court may charge reasonable fees.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>LAY ADVOCATES.</heading>
        <text>Lay advocates shall be permitted to obtain a certificate to practice before the Courts in all civil matters, traffic violations and misdemeanor criminal matters when the defendant has knowingly waived his right to an attorney. For the purposes of <cite path="|5.01.060|(e)">Section 5.01.060(e)</cite>, a misdemeanor is an offense punishable by incarceration for less than a year and/or fine not exceeding One Thousand dollars ($1,000) or both. The provisions of <cite path="|5.01.060|(d)|(1)">Section 5.01.060(d)(1)</cite>, (C)-(F) shall also apply to lay advocates. The Chief Judge shall establish the qualifications for certification of lay advocates to appear in cases before the Trial Court.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|I|6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.02</num>
    <heading>Rules of Criminal Procedure</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.010</num>
      <heading>GENERAL PROVISIONS</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>SIGNATURE.</heading>
        <text>Defined. The act of putting a person's name at the end of an instrument to attest its validity. A signature may be written by hand, printed, stamped, typewritten, or engraved and whatever mark, symbol, or device one may choose to employ as representative of himself is sufficient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>WORDS USED IN PRESENT TENSE.</heading>
        <text>Unless otherwise provided, words used in <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite> in the present tense include the future as well as the present. Words used in the masculine include the feminine and the neuter, and plural includes the singular and vice-versa. The term "writing" includes the printing. The term "oath" includes affirmation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>SPECIAL PROVISIONS CONTROL GENERAL PROVISIONS.</heading>
        <text>In construing <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, each general provision shall be controlled by any special provision on the same subject if a conflict exists.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.020</num>
      <heading>COMMENCEMENT OF CRIMINAL PROCEEDINGS</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>COMPLAINT, DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>A Complaint is a written charge presented by the Prosecutor to the Trial Court judge having jurisdiction, that a person has committed a specified offense in violation of Kiowa Criminal Law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>CONTENTS OF COMPLAINT.</heading>
        <text>Each Complaint must contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The name of the jurisdiction where it is filed and the Trial Court within which it is brought.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The names of the parties. If the names of all the defendants are not known, the complainant may add names as needed.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A statement signed by the complainant of the acts constituting the offense, and the time and place of the commission of the offense, be as near as may be ascertained, in ordinary and concise language.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>FILING OF COMPLAINT.</heading>
        <text>The Prosecutor shall file a complaint with the Court and the Clerk shall mark thereon the date of filing same.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>ASSIGNMENT OF CRIMINAL ACTIONS.</heading>
        <text>Criminal Actions that include allegations of an offense or offenses, which could result in a sentence of incarceration for more than one (1) year as defined in <cite path="|13.04.010">Section 13.04.010</cite>in <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, shall only be heard by the Chief Judge, Senior Associate Judge, or a Pro-Tem Judge.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.030</num>
      <heading>ARREST, DELIVERY ON WARRANT, AND HOT PURSUIT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>ARREST - DEFINED; PERSONS QUALIFIED TO MAKE; AID MAY BE REQUIRED.</heading>
        <text>Arrest is the taking of any person subject to the jurisdiction of the Kiowa Tribal Courts in custody and held to answer for a Tribal offense. An arrest may be made by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A duly authorized police officer under a warrant as provided in <cite path="|5.02.030|(b)">Section 5.02.030(b)</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A duly authorized police officer without a warrant as provided in <cite path="|5.02.030|(e)">Section 5.02.030(e)</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Any Indian must promptly aid an officer in the execution of an arrest if the police officer commands his aid.</text>
        </para>
        <text>A police officer may detain a non-Indian for purposes of determining whether a crime(s) has been committed and the appropriate jurisdiction to address such crime(s).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>WARRANT OF ARREST.</heading>
        <text>A Warrant of Arrest is a written order signed by a Trial Court judge commanding the arrest of any person subject to the jurisdiction of the Kiowa Tribal Courts. The warrant must specify the name of the person, or a description by which the person can be identified with reasonable certainty, if the name of the person is not known. It must also state the offense or offenses charged and the date it was issued. A Warrant of Arrest shall not be valid outside the limits of the Kiowa Tribe's jurisdiction as defined in <cite path="|5.01.040|(a)">Section 5.01.040(a)</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite> but shall be subject to extradition as agreed upon between the Tribe and the various foreign jurisdictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>DIRECTION TO PEACE OFFICER; EXECUTION.</heading>
        <text>The Warrant may be directed to any law enforcement officer as defined in <cite path="|5.01.060|(a)">Section 5.01.060(a)</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite> and shall be executed by any qualified law officer to whom it may be delivered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>ARREST.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <heading>EXECUTION OF WARRANT.</heading>
          <text>The Warrant shall be executed by the arrest of the person. The peace officer need not have the Warrant in his possession at the time of the arrest; but must be satisfied that the arrestee is the person identified in the warrant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <heading>WITHOUT A WARRANT.</heading>
          <text>Any enforcement officer may, without a Warrant, arrest an Indian person:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>For an offense committed or attempted in his presence.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>When he has probable or reasonable cause for believing the Indian person arrested has committed an offense. He is justified in making the arrest though it is later determined that the offense had not been committed by the party arrested. When an Indian person is arrested without a warrant, the officer must inform him of his authority and the cause of the arrest, except when he is in the actual commission of an offense or when pursued and apprehended immediately after the commission of an offense.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <heading>NOTIFICATION OF RIGHTS.</heading>
          <text>At the time of making the arrest, the arresting officer must inform the defendant that he or she has the right to remain silent; that anything he says may be used against him in Court; that he may cease talking at any time he desires; and that he has a right to counsel before answering any questions regarding an alleged crime. If the defendant does not waive such rights, or requests legal counsel, the officer must not continue any interrogation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>BREAKING INTO DWELLING HOUSE OR OTHER STRUCTURE TO MAKE ARREST OR TO PROTECT A POTENTIAL VICTIM OF A CRIME.</heading>
        <text>Any Enforcement officer having authority to make an arrest may break open an outer or inner door or window of a dwelling house or other structure for the purpose of making an arrest, or where a reasonable person would have reason to believe that a person's life or limb is in immediate danger.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>PROMPT APPEARANCE OF DEFENDANT BEFORE A TRIAL COURT JUDGE.</heading>
        <text>An officer making an arrest shall take the defendant without undue delay before a Trial Court judge for arraignment. When a defendant arrested without a warrant is brought before the Court, a complaint shall be filed without delay. The defendant arrested shall be arraigned at the next regularly scheduled session of the Court. Any person brought before the Court at the session immediately following the arrest shall be considered to have been presented before the Court without undue delay.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>RETURN OF WARRANT.</heading>
        <text>Upon service of the Warrant of Arrest, or upon failure to find and apprehend the accused, the officer to whom the Warrant is directed shall endorse and return it to the Trial Court for filing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>EXTRADITION.</heading>
        <text>The Chairman is hereby empowered to negotiate for the extradition of persons accused of criminal offenses, both to and from the Territory of the Kiowa Tribe, with any state, county, municipal jurisdiction or Indian Tribe, and to enter into reciprocal agreements that are substantially in the form attached. Such agreements shall be the law of the Tribe until the date or expiration thereof or until rescinded by both the Chairman and the Legislature.</text>
        <include>
          <text class="center">
            <strong>
              <u>RECIPROCAL EXTRADITION AGREEMENT</u>
            </strong>
          </text>
          <text>This agreement, entered into this ________________ day of ________, between the Kiowa Tribe and __________________________________, by and through their authorized representatives, is intended to provide a practical, workable framework in which said jurisdictions can obtain the extradition, for purposes of criminal prosecution, of persons violating the laws of either jurisdiction and fleeing to or found in the territory of the other.</text>
          <section>
            <num>1</num>
            <heading>Definitions</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(1)</num>
              <text>"Executive Authority" means the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe, in the case of the This agreement, entered into this ____________________ day of ________, between the Kiowa Tribe and ____________________________________, by and through their authorized representatives, is intended to provide a practical, workable framework in which said jurisdictions can obtain the extradition, for purposes of criminal prosecution, of persons violating the laws of either jurisdiction and fleeing to or found in the territory of the other.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(2)</num>
              <text>"Territorial Jurisdiction" means all lands and property within the limits of the territorial jurisdiction of either party hereto.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(3)</num>
              <text>"Criminal offense" means any act or failure to act which is defined by the law of the requesting jurisdiction to be criminal, and in the case of the Kiowa Tribe shall include any act or failure to act made criminal by any code, ordinance or law of the Kiowa Tribe, and in the case of requesting jurisdictions, shall mean any act or failure to act which is declared to be, or punished as if it were, a felony. "Criminal offense" shall include a sentence of imprisonment for a criminal offense from which the accused person has fled or escaped before completing or being released by lawful procedure.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(4)</num>
              <text>Requesting jurisdiction" means the jurisdiction which initiates a request for the other jurisdiction to turn over a person accused of a criminal offense.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(5)</num>
              <text>"Responding jurisdiction" means the jurisdiction which receives a request to turn over a person accused of a criminal offense.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(6)</num>
              <text>"Prosecuting authority" means the officer of either jurisdiction charged with the duty to prosecute the criminal offense for which extradition is sought.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>2</num>
            <text>Persons charged with criminal offense to be delivered upon demand.</text>
            <text>Subject to the laws applicable to each party hereto, and except as otherwise provided in this agreement, the executive authority of each jurisdiction which is a party hereto shall cause to be arrested and delivered up to the executive authority of the requesting jurisdiction, any person within the territorial jurisdiction of the responding jurisdiction accused of committing a criminal offense as defined herein within the territorial jurisdiction of the requesting jurisdiction, upon receipt of a request for extradition as specified herein.</text>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>3</num>
            <heading>Request for Extradition.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(7)</num>
              <text>The request for extradition shall be in writing and addressed from the executive authority of the requesting jurisdiction to the executive authority of the responding jurisdiction and shall request the extradition of a person charged with committing a criminal offense in the requesting jurisdiction and having thereafter fled from the requesting jurisdiction.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(8)</num>
              <text>The request for extradition must be accompanied by certified copies of the following documents:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(A)</num>
                <text>The indictment, information, or criminal complaint, together with any affidavits relating thereto, or, in the case of the failure to serve or complete a sentence or imprisonment lawfully imposed, the judgment and sentence and any affidavits or documents relating thereto plus a certificate of the executive authority of the requesting jurisdiction that the person requested has escaped from the confinement, or has otherwise unlawfully failed to complete same.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(B)</num>
                <text>A warrant of arrest issued by the requesting jurisdiction.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(9)</num>
              <text>The indictment, information or criminal complaint, together with supporting affidavits, must substantially charge the person requested with having committed a criminal offense as defined herein under the law of the requesting jurisdiction.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(10)</num>
              <text>The authenticity of the documents submitted and the validity and good faith of the request for extradition must be certified to in the request by the executive authority of the requesting jurisdiction.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>4</num>
            <text>Procedure Upon Receipt of a Request for Extradition</text>
            <text>The executive authority of the responding jurisdiction shall, within five (5) days after receipt of a request for extradition, do one of the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(11)</num>
              <text>Forward the request, with his approval endorsed thereon, to a judge of his jurisdiction empowered to issue warrants of arrest; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(12)</num>
              <text>Return the request to the executive authority of the requesting jurisdiction with his reasons for not approving the request endorsed thereon, provided however, that the executive authority shall not inquire into the guilt or innocence of the accused as a condition to granting or withholding approval.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>5</num>
            <heading>Arrest of Accused Person</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(13)</num>
              <text>Upon receipt of a request for extradition with the approval of the executive authority of the responding jurisdiction endorsed thereon, the judge of the responding jurisdiction shall issue a warrant of arrest for the person named in the request, and deliver said warrant of arrest to the law enforcement officers of the responding jurisdiction having authority to make arrests.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(14)</num>
              <text>The warrant of arrest so issued shall substantially conform to the requirements for such documents in the responding jurisdiction and shall recite the facts necessary to the validity of its issuance.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(15)</num>
              <text>Such warrants of arrest shall authorize the arrest of the accused at any time or place within the territorial jurisdiction of the responding jurisdiction in the manner provided for other arrests in that jurisdiction, and the authority of the officers executing said warrant shall be the same as when making other, arrests.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>6</num>
            <heading>Procedure upon Arrest</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(16)</num>
              <text>As soon as practicable after the arrest of the accused, he shall be taken before the judge issuing the warrant of arrest and, after confirming his identity, there he shall be advised of the cause of the arrest, and, if he so desires, given an opportunity to obtain counsel.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(17)</num>
              <text>If the accused or his counsel desires to test the legality of the arrest, a hearing to determine such issue shall be scheduled and held as soon as is practicable. Notice of such hearing-shall be given to the prosecuting authority of the responding jurisdiction, and to the agent of the requesting jurisdiction into whose custody the accused would otherwise be delivered.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(18)</num>
              <text>No person arrested under this agreement shall be delivered up to the requesting jurisdiction until he has either had a hearing to test the legality of his arrest, or has, in open court, made an informed waiver of such hearing.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(19)</num>
              <text>Persons arrested pursuant to this agreement shall be incarcerated in the local jail of the respective jurisdiction, as in the case of regular arrests.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(20)</num>
              <text>Any person arrested pursuant to this agreement shall be given the opportunity to make bail in any case where his delivery to the requesting jurisdiction is not imminent. Such bail shall be in amount sufficient to reasonably assure the appearance of the accused at a time and place specified by the court. Forfeiture of bail and arrest for nonappearance, where appropriate, may be made as in other cases.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>7</num>
            <text>Procedure if Prosecution is pending in the Responding Jurisdiction</text>
            <text>If a criminal prosecution has been instituted in the responding jurisdiction against the person whose extradition is sought, the executive authority of the responding jurisdiction, in his discretion, may either surrender the accused to the requesting jurisdiction or hold him until he has been tried and discharged or convicted and punished in the responding jurisdiction.</text>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>8</num>
            <heading>Manner of Initiating Requests for Extradition</heading>
            <text>The prosecuting authority of each jurisdiction shall have authority to initiate requests for extradition, to administer the details thereof, and to designate officers to receive persons extradited from the other jurisdiction.</text>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>9</num>
            <heading>Prosecution in Requesting Jurisdiction</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(21)</num>
              <text>A person extradited under this agreement shall be given the same rights and privileges under the laws of the requesting jurisdiction as any other person accused of a criminal offense by that jurisdiction.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(22)</num>
              <text>Criminal prosecution in the requesting jurisdiction shall be limited to the criminal offense specified in the request for extradition and any lesser included offenses.</text>
            </para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>10</num>
            <heading>Sovereignty</heading>
            <text>Nothing in this agreement or in the implementation hereof shall be deemed to be a grant, cession or waiver of any of the sovereign governmental rights, powers, or jurisdiction of either party hereto, including sovereign immunity.</text>
          </section>
          <section>
            <num>11</num>
            <heading>Duration of Agreement.</heading>
            <para>
              <num>(23)</num>
              <text>This agreement shall become effective upon its execution by the executive authorities of the parties hereto.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(24)</num>
              <text>This agreement shall remain in effect until canceled by notification from the executive authority of either jurisdiction to the other.</text>
            </para>
            <text>Done at ___________________________ on the day and year first above written.</text>
            <text>KIOWA TRIBE						_____________________________</text>
            <text>By: __________________________			By: __________________________</text>
            <text>Chairman</text>
          </section>
        </include>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <heading>HOT PURSUIT DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>For the purpose of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, the term "hot pursuit" shall mean the act of chasing or following a person by a law enforcement officer who has reason to believe the person has committed a violation of the laws of the Kiowa Tribe, beyond the boundaries of the Trial Court's jurisdiction with the intent to arrest the person for such violation. The term shall include and be limited to immediate and uninterrupted pursuit. Any law enforcement officer as defined in <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite> shall have the authority to engage in hot pursuit to apprehend and return to this jurisdiction and to incarcerate and charge such person with a violation of the Kiowa Criminal Code.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.040</num>
      <heading>SEARCH WARRANT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>SEARCH WARRANT DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>A search warrant is a written Order signed by a Trial Court judge, directing any enforcement officer, as designated by <cite path="|5.01.060|(a)|(4)">Section 5.01.060(a)(4)</cite> of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, to search for items or articles designated in the warrant and to bring them before the Trial Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>ISSUANCE &amp; CONTENTS.</heading>
        <text>A search warrant shall only be issued upon probable cause, supported by oath or affirmation, naming or describing with particularity the person, the items or articles to be seized, the place to be searched, and the reason or reasons for its issuance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>EXECUTION OF WARRANT, OFFICERS AUTHORIZED TO BREAK IN STRUCTURE.</heading>
        <text>A search warrant may be served by any duly authorized enforcement officer during any time of the day or night unless the Trial Court finds sufficient reason to limit the time in which the warrant may be served and so endorses the warrant. The officer may break open any building, structure, or container while serving a warrant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>TIME LIMIT; EXECUTION OF WARRANT; VOID AT EXPIRATION.</heading>
        <text>A search warrant must be executed and returned to the Trial Court judge by whom it was issued within ten (10) days. The warrant is void after the expiration of that time, unless extended at the discretion of the Trial Court, and so endorsed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>INVENTORY.</heading>
        <text>The officer must immediately return the warrant to the Trial Court judge, as set forth in <cite path="|5.02.040|(d)">Section 5.02.040(d)</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, together with a complete inventory of the items or articles taken. The inventory must be made before witnesses or in the presence of the person from whose possession it was taken. The Trial Court shall deliver a copy of the inventory to the person from whose possession the items or articles were taken.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>SEARCH &amp; SEIZURE INCIDENTAL TO ARREST.</heading>
        <text>All reasonable searches and seizures that are incidental to a legal arrest are valid.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.050</num>
      <heading>BAIL</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>BAIL DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>Bail is setting at liberty a person arrested or imprisoned on security being taken for his appearance. His sureties shall be regarded as custodians of the principal's person. This provision is applicable only to offenses over which the Tribe has jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>BAILABLE OFFENSES.</heading>
        <text>All defendants, as a matter of right, are bailable before conviction, by the posting of sufficient cash or surety bail bond, and after conviction if an appeal is pending. If bail is required and not met, the defendant shall be incarcerated until his case is heard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>BAIL SET; MAXIMUM AMOUNT.</heading>
        <text>Bail shall be set by the judge upon the showing of probable cause by the prosecutor or complainant. Bail shall be filed in such amount and in such form as, in the judgment of the Court, will insure the presence of the defendant in Court at the time of trial, having due regard for the nature and circumstances of the offense charged, the character and reputation of the defendant and the previous criminal record of the defendant. In no case shall the bail exceed five times the maximum cash penalty for each offense for which the defendant has been charged.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>TAKING OF BAIL; ENTERED BY CLERK.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court shall accept sufficient cash or surety bond for the appearance of the defendant. Upon filing, the Clerk shall enter in the register of actions the date and amounts of the bond or name or names of the surety or sureties thereon and the amount of the bond.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>DISCHARGE OF DEFENDANT; BAIL FURNISHED; ORDER.</heading>
        <text>If the defendant is in custody, upon the execution of the requisite recognizance or bail bond to the Tribe, the Court must issue a written order for the defendant's discharge and upon the delivery of such order to the proper officer the defendant must be discharged.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>INCREASE OR DECREASE OF BAIL BOND; COMMITMENT ON DEFAULT.</heading>
        <text>When good cause has been shown to the Trial Court that a person previously admitted to bail on any such charge is about to abscond, has violated the conditions of his release or, has been charged with a subsequent offense, the Court may reconsider the amount of bail and may remand him to the custody of the jail pending a bail hearing. The Court may also, for good cause, reduce the amount of the bail after a hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>ARREST OF DEFENDANT BY SURETY.</heading>
        <text>At any time before the defendant is required to appear and at any place within the Territory, for the purpose of surrendering the defendant, the surety may himself arrest the defendant, or, by written authority endorsed on a certified copy of the bond, may empower any person of suitable age and discretion to do so and cause the delivery of the defendant before the Court forthwith, whereupon said bond shall be released.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>FORFEITURE OF BAIL.</heading>
        <text>If the defendant fails to appear for trial or when his personal appearance in Court is lawfully required, the Court may direct an entry of such failure to be made in the record, and the surety bond, or the money deposited instead of the bond, may be forfeited without further proceedings and the Court will thereafter issue a warrant for the arrest of the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <heading>RETURN OF CASH OR SURETY BOND.</heading>
        <text>Any security given by a surety or by the defendant must be returned upon the return of a not guilty verdict or upon the execution of the sentence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <heading>RELEASE.</heading>
        <text>At arraignment, the Court, in its discretion, may release a defendant upon the defendant's own recognizance (OR). In determining whether to grant or release or set bond, the Court may consider the following factors:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Whether the defendant accurately identified himself to the Court and Law Enforcement or used a false name or date of birth.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The nature and circumstances of the current charge, including whether the offense allegedly involved the use of force or violence, the risk of danger to any person or the community if the defendant is released on his own recognizance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The defendant's prior criminal history, if any, and whether, at the time of the current arrest or offense, the defendant was on probation, parole, or on other release pending trial, sentencing, or appeal for an offense.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The nature and extent of defendant's family relationships and ties to the Kiowa community.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Defendant's employment status and work history.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <heading>BAIL FOR JUVENILE PERSONS.</heading>
        <text>No bail shall be required of any person who has not reached his sixteenth birthday. Custody and detention of minors under the age of sixteen shall be governed by Kiowa Children's Code.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.060</num>
      <heading>ARRAIGNMENT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>ARRAIGNMENT DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>Arraignment consists of the reading by the Court of the complaint to the defendant and delivering to him a true copy thereof and of the endorsements thereon and asking him whether he pleads guilty or not guilty to the offense charged in the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>PROCEDURE AT ARRAIGNMENT.</heading>
        <text>Arraignment shall be conducted in open Court, including by use of remote video and audio instruments in accordance with Court rules and if available and shall consist of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Providing the accused with a copy of the complaint and reading the complaint to the accused in open court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Informing the accused of the substance of the charges and the law establishing the offense and fixing the penalty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Informing the accused of his rights to counsel at his own expense, if he so desires, or to the possibility of a Court appointed counsel at no cost if he qualifies.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Calling on him to plead to the charges.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Asking the accused if he understands his rights and have the accused sign a form affirming that he has been informed of those rights and ensuring the accused understands the charges, the potential punishment and the right to a trial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>PLEAS.</heading>
        <text>The defendant may plead, "guilty," "not guilty," "not guilty by reason of former jeopardy," or "not guilty by reason of insanity." If the defendant wishes to plead "not guilty," he may demand a jury trial. After a plea of "not guilty," the Court shall set a date for trial which shall allow sufficient time for defendant to prepare his defense. If the defendant refuses to plead, a plea of "not guilty" will be entered for him by the Court. If the defendant wishes to plead "guilty," he may be sentenced immediately or within a reasonable time thereafter. A plea made to the Court must be made in open court with the defendant himself in Court. When the defendant pleads a former jeopardy and shall have been acquitted or convicted upon complaint, the conviction or acquittal is a bar to another complaint for the offense charged in the former, or for an attempt to commit the same, or an offense necessarily included therein of which he might have been convicted under that complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.070</num>
      <heading>PRE-TRIAL MOTIONS</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>MOTIONS DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>A motion is the formal mode in which a party submits a proposed measure or resolution for the consideration and action of the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>MOTION TO SET ASIDE THE COMPLAINT.</heading>
        <text>The complaint must be set aside by the Tribal Court upon the defendant's motion, prior to a plea, in the following cases:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Where it is found not to comply with the requirements of <cite path="|5.02.020|(b)">Section 5.02.020(b)</cite>of <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>That the defendant has been charged or committed without reasonable or probable cause.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>When the Court has determined that it has no jurisdiction over the person or the offense.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>ORDER SETTING ASIDE COMPLAINT NOT BAR TO SUBSEQUENT PROSECUTION.</heading>
        <text>An order to set aside the complaint is no bar to future prosecution for the same offense, except when the complaint was set aside for a lack of jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>MOTION WAIVED BY FAILURE TO MOVE TO SET ASIDE COMPLAINT.</heading>
        <text>If the motion to set aside the complaint is not made before the defendant's plea, the defendant is precluded from afterwards making the motion, except for a motion of lack of jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>PRE-TRIAL MOTIONS HEARD AT TIME MADE, EXCEPT GOOD CAUSE POSTPONEMENT.</heading>
        <text>All pre-trial motions must be ruled upon at the time they are made unless for good cause the Court postpones the hearing to another time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>MOTION FOR A BILL OF PARTICULARS.</heading>
        <text>The defendant may make a motion for a bill of particulars in order to obtain facts other than those specified in the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>MOTION TO SUPPRESS EVIDENCE.</heading>
        <text>A defendant has the right to file with the Trial Court a motion to suppress evidence which he contends has been obtained in an unlawful manner. The evidence in question may be a tangible item or an intangible item. If the Court is satisfied that the evidence has been unlawfully obtained, it shall order the evidence suppressed. If the Court decides that the evidence was lawfully obtained, it may be used against the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.080</num>
      <heading>TRIAL, GENERAL PROVISIONS</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>
          <u>CRIMINAL ACTION DEFI</u>
        </text>
        <text>NED. A criminal action is prosecuted by the Tribe as a party against a person for punishment for offenses charged in the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>IRREGULARITIES, MISTAKES OMISSIONS HAVE NO LEGAL EFFECT UNLESS ACTUALLY PREJUDICIAL.</heading>
        <text>Neither a departure from the form or mode prescribed in <cite path="|5.02.080">this section</cite> in respect to any pleading or proceedings nor an error or mistake therein renders it invalid, unless it has prejudiced the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>SUMMONING JURORS &amp; WITNESSES.</heading>
        <text>The Trial Court shall have the power to issue summons to witnesses and jurors. The summons must contain the reason for summoning the person and the number of days the person will be required to be present. If the juror or witness is summoned and appears in court as required, he shall receive a sum for each day that he is required to attend as a juror or witness, to be set by the Chief Judge. Any fees paid to jurors or witnesses shall be taxed as costs against the defendant, if found guilty. Juror and witness fees shall be paid by the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>TRIAL BY JURY OR BY THE COURT.</heading>
        <text>Cases shall be tried by the Court unless the defendant shall file with the Clerk of the Court a written request for a jury trial not less than ten (10) after his arraignment. The jury shall consist of six (6) persons and shall be selected randomly from the Kiowa membership list.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>RIGHTS OF ACCUSED.</heading>
        <text>In all criminal prosecutions, the accused person shall have the right to defend himself in person or, at his own expense, by counsel; to demand the nature and cause of the accusation against him face to face; to have compulsory process served for obtaining witnesses in his behalf; and to a speedy public trial by an impartial jury. No person shall be compelled in any criminal case to give evidence against himself or be twice put in jeopardy for the same offense; upon request, the accused or a juror shall be entitled to an interpreter.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>PRESENCE OF THE DEFENDANT.</heading>
        <text>The defendant in a criminal case has the right be present in Court at every stage of the proceedings, including the empaneling of the jury and the return of the verdict, where trial is by jury, and at the imposition of the sentence.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>WAIVER OF RIGHTS.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Notwithstanding the rights enumerated in <cite path="|5.02.080|(f)">Section 5.02.080(f)</cite>, a defendant who is properly notified of the date of the trial and voluntarily absent shall be deemed to have waived the right to be present at trial and at the return of the verdict. Therefore, the trial to a jury or the Court may proceed in absentia and the verdict recorded by the Clerk of the Court. If the jury or Judge renders a guilty verdict, a bench warrant shall issue for the arrest of the defendant and he shall be sentenced within 30 days after he is apprehended of voluntarily appears on the warrant.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Rule 43 of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure is hereby superseded and shall be replaced with the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text><u>When Required</u>.</text>
            <text>Unless this rule, Rule 5, or Rule 10 provides otherwise, the defendant must be present at:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>the initial appearance, the initial arraignment, and the plea;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>every trial stage, including jury empanelment and the return of the verdict; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>sentencing.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text><u>When Not Required. A defendant need not be present under any of the following circumstances</u>:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>Organizational Defendant.</text>
              <text>The defendant is an organization represented by counsel who is present.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text><u>Offense</u>.</text>
              <text>The offense is punishable by fine or by imprisonment for not more than six months, or both, and with the defendant's written consent, the court permits arraignment, plea, trial, and sentencing to occur in the defendant's absence.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text><u>Conference or Hearing on a Legal Question</u>.</text>
              <text>The proceeding involves only a conference or hearing on a question of law.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text><u>Sentence Correction</u>.</text>
              <text>The proceeding involves the correction or reduction of sentence under Rule 35 or 18 U.S.C.  3582(c).</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text><u>Waiving Presence</u>.</text>
              <text>A defendant waives the right to be present under the following circumstances:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(I)</num>
                <text>when the defendant is voluntarily absent, if the court has informed the defendant of an obligation to be present and remain during trial.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(II)</num>
                <text>when the court warns the defendant that it will remove the defendant from the courtroom for disruptive behavior, but the defendant persists in conduct that justifies removal from the courtroom.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>CALENDAR; CLERK OF COURT'S DUTIES.</heading>
        <text>The Clerk of the Court must keep a calendar of all criminal actions pending in the Court, listing them according to the date of the filing of the complaint, specifying the offense charged and whether the defendant is in custody or on bail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <heading>SETTING CASES FOR TRIAL; MAXIMUM TIME; CONTINUANCES; PROOF REQUIRED; LENGTH; PRECEDENCE OF CRIMINAL CASES.</heading>
        <text>The Court shall set all criminal cases for trial as soon as possible after the date of entry of the plea of the defendant. No continuances of the trial shall be granted except upon affirmative proof in open court, and upon reasonable notice, that the ends of justice require a continuance. The defendant shall be entitled to a reasonable continuance, but such continuance shall not exceed thirty (30) days, unless for good cause. Criminal cases shall be given precedence over civil cases.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <heading>DEATH, ILLNESS; SUBSTITUTIONS AUTHORITY OF SUBSTITUTE JUDGE.</heading>
        <text>After the commencement of the trial of a criminal action or proceeding, if the judge presiding at such trial shall die, become ill, or for any other reason be unable to proceed with and finish the trial, another judge may proceed with and finish the trial. If no other judge is available, then the Clerk of that Court shall adjourn the Court until such time as by stipulation in writing between the parties to the proceeding, a judge shall be agreed upon by them and shall arrive to complete the trial. The judge authorized by <cite path="|5.02.080|(j)">Section 5.02.080(j)</cite> shall proceed with and complete the trial and has the same power, authority, and jurisdiction as if the trial had originally commenced before him.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|8" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.090</num>
      <heading>FORMATION OF THE JURY</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>QUALIFICATIONS OF JURORS.</heading>
        <text>The basic qualifications of a juror shall be: Any person who is a duly enrolled member of the Kiowa Tribe; who has reached his twenty-first (21st) birthday; and has been a resident within the Territory of the Kiowa Tribe for ninety (90) days; and who is not under any legal disability; and who has not been convicted of a felony or major offense in any jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>JURY PANEL EXCUSED.</heading>
        <text>It is within the Trial Court's discretion whether a jury summoned for the trial prior to a continuation or postponement shall remain or a new jury panel is selected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>CHALLENGES DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>A challenge is an objection made to the trial jurors and can be made either against the entire panel, or individual jurors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>PANEL DEFINED.</heading>
        <text>A panel is a list of jurors returned by the board of jury selectors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>CHALLENGE TO PANEL DEFINED, WHO MAY CHALLENGE AND REASON FOR CHALLENGE.</heading>
        <text>A challenge to the panel is a written objection made regarding all the jurors returned and may be made by either party. The panel may be challenged when there is an error in the procedure used in summoning the jurors, or bias can be shown.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <heading>CHALLENGES TO INDIVIDUAL JURORS.</heading>
          <text>A challenge to an individual juror is an objection which may be taken orally and is either for cause or peremptory.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>ORDER AND TIME FOR EXERCISING CHALLENGES.</heading>
        <text>All challenges for cause must be taken first by the defendant and then by the Tribe. Peremptory challenges may be taken by either party at any time during the seating of the jury and before the jury is sworn.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>CHALLENGE FOR CAUSE.</heading>
        <text>A challenge for cause may be made by the Tribe or by the defendant and must specify the facts constituting the causes thereof. It may be made for any of the following causes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Having served as a juror in a civil action brought against the defendant for the act charged as an offense.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Being a party adverse to the defendant in a civil action or having complained against or been accused by him in a criminal action.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Having formed or expressed an opinion as to the guilt or innocence of the defendant based on information the juror has learned, whether true or false, concerning the defendant's alleged criminal conduct.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>A relationship between the juror and the defendant that in the opinion of the judge would cause the juror to be unable to render an impartial decision.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>FAILURE TO CHALLENGE FOR CAUSE.</heading>
        <text>Failure to challenge for cause shall con stitute a waiver of the basis for challenge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <heading>JURY SELE CTI ON.</heading>
        <text>The Chief Judge, in cooperation with the Clerk of the Court, and the Director of Enrollment Department of the Tribe, will establish rules regarding Jury Selection.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <heading>PEREMPTORY CHALLENGE, PARTIES WHO MAY TAKE, FORM, DEFINITION.</heading>
        <text>A peremptory challenge can be taken by either party and may be made orally. It is an objection to a juror for which no reason need be given, but upon which the Court may exclude him.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <heading>PEREMPTORY CHALLENGE; NUMBER JOINT DEFENDANTS.</heading>
        <text>The defendant is entitled to two (2) and the Tribe to two (2) peremptory challenges. If two or more defendants are jointly tried for any public offense, the Tribe and the defendants shall be entitled to two (2) peremptory challenges and on the part of the defendants must be exercised jointly.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <heading>VACANCY FILLED.</heading>
        <text>After each challenge, sustained for cause or made peremptorily, another juror shall be called, may be challenged for cause, and shall be subject to peremptory challenge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <heading>JURY OATH.</heading>
        <text>When the jury has been selected, the judge shall administer to the jurors the following oath:</text>
        <text>"You and each of you do solemnly swear or affirm that you will well and truly try the issues relative to the cause now on trial according to the law and the evidence under the penalty of Perjury."</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <heading>CONTINUANCE.</heading>
        <text>If a jury trial is continued, the jury shall then be notified of the new date for trial and no further notice to them of such date is required. The penalty for failure to appear at the time to which the trial is continued is contempt of court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(o)</num>
        <heading>JURY DUTY EXEMPTION.</heading>
        <text>The following persons shall be exempt from jury service:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Members of the Tribal and Federal Police Departments.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Appointed and elected officials of the executive, legislative and judicial branches of the government of the Kiowa Tribe, as follows:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>Legislators.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>Chairman.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>Vice Chairman.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(D)</num>
            <text>Chief Judge, Senior Associate Judge, Associate Judges and Supreme Court Justices; and</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Kiowa Elders age 70 and over may file for a permanent exemption from Jury Duty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Persons with disabilities that would create an undue hardship for the juror to serve or that would unduly burden the Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The Trial Judge has the discretionary authority to excuse those who the Judge believes should be exempt from jury service.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|9" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.100</num>
      <heading>TRIAL PROCEDURE</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>ORDER OF PROCEDURE.</heading>
        <text>The jury having been selected and sworn, the trial shall proceed as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Clerk of the Trial Court judge must read the complaint and state the plea of the defendant to the jury.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Opening statements shall be given by the Tribe followed by the defendant and his counsel.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Tribe must open the case and offer evidence in support of the charge. The defendant or his counsel shall have the right to cross-examine any witness called to testify by the Tribe.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The defendant or his counsel may than open the defense and offer evidence in support thereof. The Tribe shall have the right to cross-examine any witness called by the defendant or his counsel.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>The parties may then respectively offer rebutting testimony only, unless the Court, in furtherance of justice, permits them to offer evidence upon their original case.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>When the evidence is concluded, the Tribe and the defendant or his counsel may argue the case to the Court and jury, the Tribe opening the argument and having the right to close same.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Upon the conclusion of the arguments, the Court shall charge the jury orally or in writing, stating the law of the case. However, at the beginning of the trial or from time to time during the trial and without any request from either party, the judge may give the jury such instructions on the law applicable to the case as he may deem necessary for their guidance on hearing the case.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>PRESUMPTION OF INNOCENCE; EFFECT:</heading>
        <text><u>REASONABLE DOUBT; DEFENDANT'S REFUSAL TO TESTIFY; DEFENDANT'S WAIVER OF RIGHT TO BE PRESENT</u>. A defendant in a criminal action need not testify and is presumed to be innocent until the contrary is proven. The effect of this presumption is only to place upon the Tribe the burden of proving him guilty beyond a reasonable doubt. The defendant's failure to testify on his own behalf shall in no way be construed against him nor commented upon by the Tribe. When a defendant has waived his right to be present at trial, the Court, in its discretion, may allow the Tribe to comment upon the defendant's absence and waiver.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>JOINT DEFENDANTS TRIED JOINTLY; COURT MAY DIRECT SEPARATE TRIALS.</heading>
        <text>When two or more defendants are jointly charged with an offense, they shall be prosecuted jointly, provided that the Court may, in its discretion, either upon application duly made prior to trial, or upon its own finding of good cause, direct that separate trials be held.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>INTERPRETER.</heading>
        <text>In the event that any party or witness or juror requests that an interpreter be present during the trial, the Court shall appoint an interpreter from a list supplied by the Tribal Council, who shall be paid at a rate fixed by the Court, and such sum shall be taxed as costs in the case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>VIEW OF THE PREMISES BY JURY.</heading>
        <text>It is within the Court's discretion to allow the jury to view the place in which the offense is charged to have been committed, or in which any other material fact occurred. The Court may also place the jury in the custody of the appropriate officials to bring them to the appropriate place, which shall be shown to them by a person appointed by the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>DISCHARGE OF JUROR FOR ILLNESS OR DISABILITY; NEW TRIAL.</heading>
        <text>Before the jury has returned its verdict to the Court, if a juror becomes sick, or upon other good cause shown to the Court is found to be unable to perform his duty, the Court may order him to be discharged. When a juror is discharged for any of the above reasons, the Court may, upon stipulation, proceed in the absence of said juror. In the absence of such stipulation, the jury shall be discharged, and a new jury shall be empaneled to hear the case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <heading>LAW QUESTIONS FOR COURT AND FACT QUESTIONS FOR JURY.</heading>
        <text>Questions of law are to be decided by the Court and questions of fact by the jury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <heading>INSTRUCTIONS TO JURY.</heading>
        <text>At the close of evidence or at such time during the trial as the judge directs, counsel for each party may file with the judge written instructions on the law which the party requests the judge to deliver to the jury. At the same time, copies of such requests shall be furnished to opposing counsel. The judge shall inform counsel of his proposed action upon each request prior to the arguments to the jury, but the judge shall deliver his instructions to the jury after arguments are completed. No party may assign as error any portion of the judge's charge or omission therefrom unless he makes his objection before the jury retires to consider its verdict. Objections must be given out of the hearing of the jury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <heading>POLL OF JURY BEFORE RECORDING VERDICT; EITHER PARTY AUTHORIZED; DISSENTING JUROR; FURTHER DELIBERATION; DISMISSAL OF JURY.</heading>
        <text>On the request of either party, when a verdict is rendered but before it is recorded, the jury may be polled on the request of either party or the Court. Each juror must be asked whether it is his verdict. If any juror answers in the negative, the jury must be sent out for further deliberation. If upon returning after further deliberation, the jury is polled again and a juror answers that the verdict is not his own, then the judge shall dismiss the jury and a new trial will be ordered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <heading>DIRECTION OF VERDICT OF ACQUITTAL.</heading>
        <text>At any time after the evidence on either side is closed, the Court may, upon motion of the defendant or upon its own motion, direct the jury to return a verdict of acquittal; and in the event of the failure of the jury to return such a verdict of acquittal, the Court may refuse to receive any other verdict and may discharge the jury and enter a judgment of acquittal. The denial of the motion may be reviewed upon appeal to the Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe by the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|10" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.110</num>
      <heading>SUBMISSION TO THE JURY &amp; VERDICT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>PAPERS TAKEN BY JURY.</heading>
        <text>Upon retiring for deliberation, the jury may take with it all instructions, exhibits, and papers that have been received in evidence along with any notes of the testimony taken in the trial by the jurors may be taken.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>INFORMED ON ANY POINT OF LAW.</heading>
        <text>After the jury has retired for deliberation, if there be any disagreement as to any part of the testimony or if it desires to be informed on any point of law arising in the case, it must require the officer to conduct it into Court; and upon its being brought in, the information required may be given at the discretion of the Trial Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>JURY KEPT TOGETHER.</heading>
        <text>The jury shall be under the charge of the bailiff or other officer appointed by the Court. The jury must be kept together after the cause is submitted to them by the Clerk of the Court until they have agreed upon and rendered a verdict, unless, for good cause, the judge sooner discharges them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>VERDICT.</heading>
        <text>The jury must render a general verdict of "guilty" or "not guilty" which imports a conviction or acquittal on every material allegation in the complaint. The verdict in all criminal actions must be unanimous.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>HUNG JURY.</heading>
        <text>In the event the jury is unable to agree upon a verdict, the Judge shall dismiss the jury and order a new trial.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|11" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.120</num>
      <heading>JUDGMENT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>TIME FOR SENTENCING FOLLOWING CONVICTION.</heading>
        <text>Upon a plea of guilty or a verdict of guilty, the Court shall fix a time for sentencing, which must be within a reasonable time after the verdict is rendered. Prior to judgment, the Court may request a presentence investigation to be conducted by the probation department. All presentence reports shall be filed with the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>SENTENCING:</heading>
        <text><u>IMPRISONMENT</u>. When sentence of imprisonment is entered, a signed copy thereof must be delivered to the law enforcement officer as defined in <cite path="attachments|law" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007">this Code</cite>, or other officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>PRESENCE OF DEFENDANT.</heading>
        <text>When judgment is pronounced, the defendant must be personally present.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>SUSPENSION OF SENTENCE.</heading>
        <text>The Court may, on such terms and conditions as the Court may impose, suspend the imposition of sentence and release a convicted person on probation. The probation term shall not exceed the maximum term allowed under the law violated by the defendant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>COMMUTATION OF SENTENCE.</heading>
        <text>If the Court is satisfied that justice will best be served by reducing a sentence, the Court may, at any time after one-half of the sentence has been served, commute to a lesser period any sentence imposed upon a person, upon proof that during the period of confinement the person served without misconduct and/or satisfactorily performed community service pursuant to a 2 for 1 program administered by the jail or detention facility.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>EXPUNGEMENT.</heading>
        <text><u>SETTING ASIDE JUDGMENT OF CONVICTION</u>.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Every person convicted of a criminal offense, on fulfillment of the conditions of probation or sentence and discharge of the court, may apply to the judge, to have the judgment of guilt set aside. The convicted person shall be informed of this right at the time of discharge.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The application to set aside the judgment may be made by the convicted person or by the convicted person's attorney or probation officer authorized in writing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>If the judge grants the application, the judge shall set aside the judgment of guilt, dismiss the accusations or information and order that the person be released from all penalties and disabilities resulting from the conviction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|12" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.130</num>
      <heading>PROBATION</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>CONDITION OF PROBATION.</heading>
        <text>The Court may release on probation a convicted person on such terms and conditions as are just and appropriate, taking into consideration the prior criminal record of the defendant, his background, character, financial condition, family obligation, and any other pertinent circumstances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>VIOLATION OF CONDITIONS OF PROBATION.</heading>
        <text>Any person who violated the terms and conditions of his probation may be required to serve an additional jail sentence as a condition of continuing the person on probation or the Court may terminate probation and order the defendant to serve a jail term of up to one year, with no credit for time served.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|13" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.140</num>
      <heading>NEW TRIAL</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>NEW TRIAL.</heading>
        <text>A new trial is defined as a retrial of the criminal charges in the same Court before another jury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>APPLICATION.</heading>
        <text>Application for a new trial may be made only by the defendant or his attorney and must be made before the completion of the sentence. Application must be made to the Court before which the case was tried.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>GROUNDS.</heading>
        <text>The Court, on application from the defendant or on its own motion, may grant a new trial based on the following cause or causes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>When proper evidence has been presented that the jury, has received any evidence, paper, or document out of Court not authorized by the Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>When the verdict has been decided by lot or by means other than a fair expression of opinion on the part of all the jurors.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>When the Trial Court, has refused or failed to properly instruct the jury as to the applicable law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>When as a result of any other unduly prejudicial error or cause the defendant has not received a fair and impartial trial.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>EFFECT OF A NEW TRIAL.</heading>
        <text>The granting of a new trial places the parties in the same position as if no trial has been held; all testimony must be reproduced, and the former verdict cannot be used or referred to either in the evidence or in argument.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <heading>STATUS OF THE ACCUSED PENDING NEW TRIAL.</heading>
        <text>Pending a new trial, the accused shall be entitled to bail the same as before the trial.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <heading>STAY OF EXECUTION PENDING APPEAL.</heading>
        <text>If the defendant timely appeals, the Court, in its discretion, may stay a sentence of imprisonment, fine, or probation. The Court may set the terms of any stay.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|14" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.150</num>
      <heading>CONTEMPT OF COURT</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>REASONS FOR CHARGE.</heading>
        <text>A judge may punish for contempt persons guilty of the following acts:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Disorderly, contemptuous, or insolent behavior toward the judge.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Disobedience to a subpoena, duly served, or refusing to be sworn or to answer as a witness.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Disobedience or resistance to the carrying out of a lawful order made or issued by the judge.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Rescuing or interfering with any person or property in the custody of an enforcement officer acting under an order of the Court or process of the Court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Failure to appear for jury duty, without justifiable cause, when properly notified.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>CONTEMPT COMMITTED IN PRESENCE OF JUDGE.</heading>
        <text>When contempt is committed in the immediate view and the presence of the judge it may be punished summarily. The judge must make an order reciting the facts as they occurred, and that the person proceeded against is guilty of contempt, and that he be punished as therein prescribed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>CONTEMPT COMMITTED NOT IN PRESENCE OF JUDGE.</heading>
        <text>When the contempt is not committed in the immediate view and presence of the judge, a Warrant of Arrest may be issued by such judge and the person so guilty may be arrested and brought before the judge. The judge must give the arrested person an opportunity to present his defense. The judge may then discharge him or find him guilty of contempt.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <heading>PUNISHMENT.</heading>
        <text>A judge may punish contempt of court in either criminal or civil proceedings by assessing a fine or by ordering imprisonment, or both; such fine not to exceed Five Hundred Dollars ($500.00) and/or imprisonment not to exceed forty-five (45) days plus Court costs.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|15" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.02.160</num>
      <heading>RECOGNITION AND ENFORCEMENT OF FOREIGN COURT JUDGMENTS</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <heading>DEFINITION OF TERMS.</heading>
        <text>When used in <cite path="|5.02.160">this section</cite>, unless the content otherwise indicates:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>"Foreign Court" means any court other than the Trial or Supreme Court of Kiowa Tribe, including federal, state, tribal or courts of a foreign country.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>"Foreign Judgment" means any final judgment, decree, or order by any Foreign Court, regardless of whether the judgment is for money, injunctive, declaratory, or any other relief.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>"Judgment Creditor and Judgment Holder" are synonymous and mean one who has a judgment rendered in his or her favor.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>"Judgment Debtor" means the party against whom a judgment has been rendered.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>"Rendering Jurisdiction" means the jurisdiction in which the foreign judgment was entered.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <heading>RECOGNITION OF FOREIGN JUDGMENTS.</heading>
        <text>The judgments, decrees, orders, warrants, subpoenas, records and other judicial acts or a foreign court are recognized and have the same effect and are subject to the same procedures, defenses and proceedings as judgments, decrees, orders, warrants, subpoenas, records and other judicial acts of the Trial Court, subject to the provisions of this rule.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The recognition described in this rule applies only if the foreign court has enacted an ordinance, court rule or other binding measure that obligates the foreign court to enforce the judgments, decrees, orders, warrants, subpoenas, records and other judicial acts of the Kiowa Courts.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The person seeking recognition or enforcement of a foreign judgment complies with the conditions and procedures set forth in <cite path="|5.02.160|(c)">Section 5.02.160(c)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A judgment decree, order, warrant, subpoena, record or other judicial entry of a foreign court that complies with the above conditions described in <cite path="|5.02.160|(b)|(1)">Section 5.02.160(b)(1)</cite> is presumed to be valid. To overcome this presumption, an objecting party must demonstrate that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The foreign court lacked personal or subject matter jurisdiction; or</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The judgment, decree, order, warrant, subpoena, record or other judicial acts of the foreign court</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>was obtained by fraud, duress or coercion;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>was obtained without fair notice or a fair hearing;</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>is repugnant to the public policy of the Tribe; or</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>is not final under the laws and procedures of the foreign court.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>This rule does not apply to judgments or orders that federal law requires be given full faith and credit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <heading>PROCEDURES FOR RECOGNITION OR ENFORCEMENT OF FOREIGN JUDGMENTS.</heading>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text><u>Application</u>. In accordance with the foreign judgment recognition provisions set forth in <cite path="|5.02.160|(b)">Section 5.02.160(b)</cite>, a foreign judgment that is final and conclusive is enforceable in the Trial Court pursuant to the following procedure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text><u>Registration of Foreign Judgment</u>. A person seeking enforcement of a foreign judgment shall file:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>A copy of the foreign judgment, which has been authenticated by the clerk or registrar of the foreign court in the following manner:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>The clerk or registrar of the foreign court must attest in writing that he or she:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(I)</num>
                <text>Is the clerk or registrar of the foreign court.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(II)</num>
                <text>Is the custodian of the records of the foreign court; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(III)</num>
                <text>Has compared an attached copy of the foreign judgment from the case with the original(s) on file and of record in the foreign court, and has found the copy of the foreign judgment to be a true copy of the whole of the original(s).</text>
              </para>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Upon completing the written attestation above, the clerk or registrar of the foreign court must:</text>
              <para>
                <num>(I)</num>
                <text>Sign and date the attestation.</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(II)</num>
                <text>Affix the seal of the foreign court to the attestation; and</text>
              </para>
              <para>
                <num>(III)</num>
                <text>Attach a certified copy of the original foreign judgment to the attestation.</text>
              </para>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>An affidavit by the judgment holder, or his/her attorney or lay advocate, which includes the following:</text>
            <para>
              <num>(i)</num>
              <text>The name and last known post office address of the judgment debtor and the judgment creditor.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(ii)</num>
              <text>Proof that the judgment is final and statement that no appeal is pending.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iii)</num>
              <text>A statement that no subsequent orders vacating, modifying or reversing the judgment have been entered in the rendering jurisdiction.</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(iv)</num>
              <text>Proof that the person against whom the foreign judgment has been rendered (i.e., judgment debtor) is subject to the jurisdiction of the Trial Court with regard to enforcement of the judgment; and</text>
            </para>
            <para>
              <num>(v)</num>
              <text>Proof that the court from which the foreign judgment was issued provides reciprocal recognition and enforcement to the judgments of the Trial Court.</text>
            </para>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(C)</num>
            <text>A receipt filing fee for registering the foreign judgment.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text><u>Notice of Registration of Foreign Judgment</u>. Upon the filing of the foreign judgment, attestation, affidavit and filing fee, the Clerk of the Court shall within fourteen (14) days mail a notice of the filing of the foreign judgment along with a copy of the foreign judgment, attestation, and affidavit to the judgment debtor at the address provided by the judgment creditor and shall complete a proof of service. The notice of the filing of the foreign judgment shall include the following:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>The name and post office address of the judgment holder and the judgment holder's attorney or lay advocate, if any; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>A statement giving notice that an order entering the enforcement of the foreign judgment shall be entered by the court within twenty-one (21) days of the same having been served on the judgment debtor unless the judgment debtor files written objections with the court along with a request for a hearing within twenty-one (21) days.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text><u>Notice for Written Objection</u>. A statement that gives the debtor notice that he/she has twenty-one (21) days to file written objections of either recognition or enforcement of the Judgment along with a request for hearing. If no objections is filed the court will enter an order recognizing and/or enforcing the judgment. The written objects shall include a statement of the basis for the objections.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text><u>Objections</u>; Hearing; Entry of Order When Objections. In the event that the judgment debtor files written objections within the twenty-one (21) day period set forth in (D) above along with a request for a hearing, the Clerk of the Court shall send by first- class mail a copy of the objections to the judgment holder, or his/her attorney or lay advocate. In addition, the Clerk of the Court shall send by first-class mail a notice of the hearing setting forth the date and time of hearing or the denial of such hearing to the judgment holder and judgment debtor, or their respective attorney(s) or lay advocate(s). The judgment debtor at the hearing will be required to show cause why the foreign judgment should not be recognized and/or enforced by the Trial Court. At the scheduled hearing, after reviewing all the relevant evidence concerning the foreign judgment, the court shall issue an order either granting or denying recognition and/or enforcement of the foreign judgment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text><u>Entry of Order Where No Objections</u>. In the event that the judgment debtor does not file written objections within the twenty-one (21) daytime period set forth in (D) above, an order granting the recognition and/or enforcement of the foreign judgment shall be issued by the court.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text><u>Appeal; Stay of Execution; Stay of Proceedings</u>. If the judgment debtor satisfies the court that an appeal from the foreign judgment is pending or will be taken, or that a stay of execution has been granted, the Trial Court may stay recognition and enforcement of the foreign judgment until the appeal is concluded, the time for appeal expires, or the stay of execution expires or is vacated.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text><u>Post-Judgment Proceedings Regarding Foreign Judgment; No Waiver of Immunity</u>.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(A)</num>
            <text>A foreign judgment holder may proceed to post-judgment proceedings upon entry of an order enforcing the foreign judgment by the Trial Court. The entry of the order enforcing the foreign judgment by the Trial Court shall entitle the judgment holder to enforce its judgment against the judgment debtor in any manner available to judgment creditors.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(B)</num>
            <text>The Tribe does not waive its immunity from suit with regard to the recognition and/or enforcement of a foreign judgment in any post-judgment proceedings, even when the Tribe is served as a garnishee-defendant for the wages or property of an employee who is a judgment debtor.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2020-08-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2020-007" eff="2020-08-18" path="attachments|law|II|16" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.03</num>
    <heading>Rules of Civil Procedure</heading>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.010</num>
      <heading>SCOPE OF RULES.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Scope. Except when different rules prescribed in <cite path="|5.03">this chapter</cite> specifically apply, these rules shall govern the procedure in the Trial and Supreme Courts of the Kiowa Tribe in all actions, suits, and proceedings of a civil nature and in all special proceedings established by law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Construction. These rules shall be liberally construed to secure a just, speedy, and inexpensive determination of every action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>One Form of Action. There shall be one form of action known, except in criminal cases, as a "civil action".</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|I|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.020</num>
      <heading>COMMENCEMENT OF ACTION; SERVICE OF PROCESS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Commencement of Action. A civil action is commenced by filing a complaint and serving a copy of such on the defendant or defendants as provided herein. The court shall have jurisdiction from such time as both the complaint is filed and properly served upon the defendant and a return of service is filed with the clerk.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Service of Process. Service of process shall consist of delivering to the party served a copy of the complaint along with a summons, which need not be issued by the judge or clerk, which advises the defendant that he is required to answer the complaint within 20 days (or in case the Tribe is a defendant, 60 days) or a default judgment will be entered against him.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The return of service shall be endorsed with the na.me of the person serving and the date, time, and place of service and shall be filed with the clerk.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Service may be made on a party by delivering the required papers to the party himself or upon some person of suitable. age and discretion over 14 years old at the party's home or principal place of business, or on an officer, managing agent or employee, or partner of a. non individual party.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Service by publication may be made upon order of the court for good cause shown by publishing the contents of the summons in a local newspaper of general circulation at least once per week for four weeks and by leaving an extra copy of the complaint or paper with the court for the party.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Service may be made by any law enforcement officer or other person, not a party, 18 years of age or older.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Service upon a person otherwise subject to the jurisdiction of the Kiowa Trial Court may be made anywhere in the State of Oklahoma; otherwise, service shall be made within any and all lands which are held by, .and any additional lands acquired by, the Tribe, and any lands held by the United States for the benefit of the Tribe or the People.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>If a person personally refuses to accept service, service shall be deemed performed if the person is informed of the purpose of the service and offered copies of the papers served.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>All papers required to be filed shall be served as under <cite path="|5.03.020">this section</cite> or, except for the complaint, may be served on the counselor or attorney of record for a party. Service of all papers except the complaint may be made by mail, first class postage prepaid and properly addressed.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.030</num>
      <heading>TIME.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Computation. In computing any period of time set forth herein, the day that the period is to commence from shall not be counted and the last day of the period shall be counted; provided, however, that any time period under 7 days will not include intermediate Saturdays, Sundays, or legal holidays in the period and any period which would otherwise end on a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday will be deemed to end on the next day which is not a Saturday, Sunday, or legal holiday.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Enlargement. The Court for good cause shown may enlarge the prescribed period of time within which any required act may be done.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Notice of Motions. Written motions and notices of hearing thereon, other than ones that may be heard ex parte, shall be served not later than 5 days (or where the Tribe is a party upon whom notice is served, 20 days) prior to the time specified for hearing.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Service by Mail. Whenever service is accomplished by mail, three days shall be added to the prescribed period of time, but such additional shall not cause Saturdays, Sundays, or legal holidays to be counted in the time period if they would not otherwise have been counted.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.040</num>
      <heading>PLEADINGS, MOTIONS, AND ORDERS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Pleadings. There shall be a complaint and an answer; plus, a responsive pleading shall be allowed whenever, by cross claim, counterclaim or otherwise, a party is first claimed against unless the court shall otherwise order. The court may grant additional leave to plead in the interest of narrowing and defining issues or as justice may require. b) Motions and Orders.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Motions. An application to the court for an order shall be by motion and shall be in writing, unless made during a hearing or trial, and shall set forth the relief or order sought, and the grounds therefore stated with particularity. A motion and notice of motion may be set forth together.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Orders. An order includes every directive of the court whether included in a judgment or not and may be made with or without notice to adverse parties and may be vacated or modified with or without notice.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Hearings on Motions and Orders. A motion or hearing on an order shall be automatically continued if the judge before whom it was to be heard is unable to hear it on the day specified and no other judge is available to hear it.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.050</num>
      <heading>GENERAL RULES OF PLEADING.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Claims for Relief. A pleading that sets forth a claim, for affirmative relief shall contain:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A short plain statement of the grounds upon which the court's jurisdiction depends, unless the court already has jurisdiction over the matter;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>a short, plain statement of the claim showing that the pleader is entitled to relief; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>a demand for judgment for the relief to which the pleader considers himself entitled. Such claim for relief can be in the alternative or for several types of relief.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Defenses and Denials. A party shall state in plain, concise terms the grounds upon which he bases his defense to claims pleaded against him and shall admit or deny the claims and statements upon which the adverse party relies. If he is without information or knowledge regarding a statement or claim, he shall so state and such shall be deemed to be a denial. Denials shall fairly meet the substance of the claims or statements denied and may be made as to specific parts but not all of a claim, statement, or averment. A general denial shall not be made unless the party could in good faith deny each and every claim covered thereby. A claim to which a responsive pleading is required, except for amount of damages, shall be deemed admitted unless denied; if no responsive pleading is allowed the claims of the adverse party shall be deemed denied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>General Content of Claims and Defenses. Claims and defenses shall be simply, concisely, and directly stated, but may be in alternative or hypothetical form, one or several counts or defenses, need not be consistent with one another, and may be based on legal or equitable grounds or both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Affirmative Defenses. Matters constituting an affirmative defense or avoidance shall be affirmatively set forth. When a party has mistakenly designated a defense as a counterclaim or vice versa, the court may treat the pleading as if it had been properly designated if justice so requires.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Construction of Pleadings. All pleadings shall be so construed as to do substantial justice.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.060</num>
      <heading>FORM OF PLEADINGS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Caption. Every pleading shall contain a caption containing the name of the court, the title of the action, the court file number (if known) and a designation as to what kind of pleading it is. All pleadings shall contain the names of the parties except the name of the first party on each side may be used on all pleadings except the complaint.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Paragraphs. All averments of claim or defense shall be set forth in separate numbered paragraphs each of which is limited, as nearly as possible, to a single circumstance. Claims or defenses founded upon separate transaction or occurrences should be set forth in separate counts or defenses.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Exhibits; Adoption by Reference. Statements in a pleading may be adopted by reference in a different part of the same pleading or in another pleading or in any motion. A copy of a written instrument that is an exhibit to a pleading is a part thereof for all purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Paper Used in Pleadings. Insofar as is possible, pleadings and other papers filed in any action shall be on letter size paper, double spaced, except for matters customarily single spaced, contain at least a 2-inch top margin and a 1-inch left side margin, and contain the court file number on the first page thereof. Substantial compliance with <cite path="|5.03.060">this section</cite> will be sufficient for all parties not represented by a professional attorney.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.070</num>
      <heading>DEFENSES AND OBJECTIONS</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When Presented. A defendant or other party against whom a claim has been made or affirmative relief shall have 20 days (or in the case of the Tribe, 60 days) from the date of service upon him to answer or respond to the claim.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Motions. Motions to dismiss or to make the opposing parties' pleadings more definite may be made prior to answering a claim and an answer will not be due until 10 days after the disposition of the motion by the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.080</num>
      <heading>COUNTERCLAIM OR CROSSCLAIM</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Counterclaim. A party against whom a claim is made may assert in his answer any claims he has against the party claiming against him and both claims shall be resolved at trial.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Crossclaim. A party against whom a claim is made may assert any claim he has against a co-party and have such claim resolved at trial.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Third Party Claim. A party against whom a claim is made may complain against a third party who is or may be liable for payment for performance of the claim of the opposing party and have such complaint resolved at trial.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|8" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.090</num>
      <heading>AMENDMENT OF PLEADINGS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Amendment Before Trial. A party may amend his pleadings once before the opposing party has replied or if no reply is required, not less than 20 days before the case is scheduled for trial. The opposing party may respond if appropriate and the trial date be delayed if necessary. Other amendments shall be allowed only upon motion and order of the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>At Trial. When issues or evidence not raised in the pleadings are heard at trial, the judgment may conform to such issues or evidence without the necessity of amending the pleadings.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|9" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.100</num>
      <heading>PARTIES.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Real Party in Interest. Every action shall be prosecuted in the name of the real party in interest, except a personal representative or other person in a fiduciary position can sue in his own name without joining the party for whose benefit the action is maintained.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Guardian Ad Litem. When an infant, or insane, or incompetent person who has not had a general guardian appointed is a party, the Court shall appoint a guardian ad litem to represent such person in the suit or action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Joinder of Parties. To the greatest extent possible given the limited jurisdiction of the Kiowa Trial Court, all persons or parties interested in a particular action may be jointed in the action, but failure to join a party over whom the Court has no jurisdiction will not require dismissal of the action unless it would be impossible to reach a just result without such party; otherwise, the failure to Join a party maybe taken into account to assure that justice is done.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|10" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.110</num>
      <heading>INTERVENTION.</heading>
      <text>A person may intervene and be treated in all respects as a party to an action in cases in which property in which he has an interest may be affected or a question of law or fact common to a claim of his may be litigated.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|11" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.120</num>
      <heading>SUBSTITUTION OF PARTIES.</heading>
      <text>If a party dies or becomes incompetent or transfers his interest or separates from some official capacity, a substitute party may be jointed or substituted as justice requires.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|12" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.130</num>
      <heading>DISCOVERY.</heading>
      <text>Reasonable discovery shall be permitted.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|13" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.140</num>
      <heading>JURY TRIALS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When Allowed. Trials of all civil actions shall be to the Court without a jury unless a party to the action files a request for a jury trial and plays a fee of $5,000 not less than 25 days prior to the scheduled date of trial. A judge may, upon good cause shown, waive payment of the required fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Issues Triable. Unless the requesting party specifies otherwise, all factual issues properly triable by a jury shall be decided by the jury at trial. A party requesting a jury trial may specify only those issues he wants tried to the jury, and any other party may specify, nor less than 5 days before the date scheduled for trial, any other issues he wishes to be so tried. Once any or all issues of a case have been requested for a jury trial, such request may not be withdrawn Without the consent of all the parties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Designation by Judge.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A judge may, upon his own motion, order the trial by a jury of any or all of the factual issues of a case regardless of whether or not the parties have requested such.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A judge may, upon motion of any party or on its own initiative, find that some or all of the issues designated for jury trial are not properly triable to a jury, and order that no jury trial be held on such issues.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A judge may hear and decide an issue or issues without a jury if either party to an issue fails to appear at trial, regardless of any request made for a jury trial on such issues.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|14" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.150</num>
      <heading>ASSIGNING CASES FOR TRIAL.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Assignment of Judge and Date. The Chief Judge shall determine which judge shall hear a case and shall provide by rule for the placing of cases on the court calendar with or without the request of any party provided all parties are given adequate notice of trial dates.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Postponement. Upon motion of a party, the court may in its discretion, an upon such terms as it deems just, including the payment of any cost occasioned by such postponement, postpone a trial or proceeding upon good cause shown.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|15" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.160</num>
      <heading>DISMISSAL OF ACTION.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Voluntary Dismissal. Prior to the responsive pleading of a party against whom a claim has been made or motion to dismiss or for summary judgment on such claim, the party making the claim may file a notice of dismissal and his claims shall be deemed dismissed without prejudice. In all other circumstances a party may move the court to dismiss his own clam and the court shall do so either with or without prejudice as is just and proper given the stage of the proceedings, provided, however, if a cross or counterclaim has been filed against the moving party, the judge shall dismiss the claim only when the consent of the adverse party or only if it appears that the other party can prosecute his claim independently without undue additional hardship.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Involuntary Dismissal. A party against whom a claim has been made may move the court to dismiss the claim of the adverse party upon any of the following grounds:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>failure of the adverse party to pursue prosecution of his claim; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Failure of the adverse party to comply substantially with these rules; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>failure of the adverse party to comply with an order of the court; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>at the close of the presentation of the other party's evidence and without prejudicing his own right to present evidence, failure of the opposing party to establishing a right to relief based on the facts and law presented.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>whenever dismissal appears proper based upon a failure to provide a claim.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <text>Such dismissal shall be deemed an adjudication of the merits of the issue dismissed unless the court shall, for good cause shown order otherwise. The court may postpone ruling on a motion to dismiss for failure to establish a right to any relief until the close of all the evidence.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The court may order a party moving to dismiss his own claim to pay the costs of the adverse party if the proceeding has progressed beyond the pleading stage and may order payment of costs in other circumstances where such is deemed appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|16" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.170</num>
      <heading>CONSOLIDATION; SEPARATE TRIALS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Consolidation. The court may, upon motion of any party or its own motion, order some or all of the issues of separate actions tried together when there is a common issue of fact or law relating the actions or if such will tend to avoid unnecessary cost or delay. b) Separate Trials. The court may, to avoid prejudice or in furtherance of convenience, order a separate trial of a claim or issue.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|17" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.180</num>
      <heading>EVIDENCE.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Form and Admissibility. At all hearings and trials, the testimony of witnesses shall be taken orally under oath, unless otherwise provided in these rules. All evidence admissible under general rules of evidence or as specified elsewhere in tribal ordinances shall be admissible and the competency of witnesses to testify shall be similarly determined.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Examination and Cross Examination.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A party may use leading questions against an adverse party or hostile witness or whenever such appears reasonably necessary to elicit testimony from witnesses of tender years or poor ability to communicate.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A party may call any person to a witness and examine any witness so called on any matter relevant to the action. A party may impeach his own witness.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Cross examination shall be limited to the general scope of direct examination, provided, however, that full examination of all witnesses shall be allowed on direct or cross examination to assure complete development of all relevant facts.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Physical Evidence. Written documents and other physical evidence shall be received upon being identified and a showing of relevance to the action.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Official Documents. Official documents or an official law record or copy thereof may be admitted into evidence upon the testimony of an official having custody or official knowledge thereof or without such testimony if the document or record or copy thereof is accompanied by a certificate identifying such thing and stating that it is a true and correct representation of what it purports to be.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Record of Excluded Evidence. In an action tried to a jury, excluded evidence may upon request be included in the record for purposes of appeal and excluded oral testimony shall be put into evidence by means of an offer of proof made out of the hearing of the jury. In an action tried only to the court, the judge may receive such, excluded testimony into the record.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|18" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.190</num>
      <heading>SUBPOENAS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Issuance. Subpoenas for attendance of witnesses or production of documents or things shall be issued by the clerk of the Trial Court and served by any police officer or other persons not a party over 18 years of age.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Failure to Appear. A person who has been properly served with a subpoena and fails to appear or produce may be deemed in contempt of court and/or the Court may order his arrest for the offense of Failure to Obey a Lawful Order of the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|19" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.200</num>
      <heading>JURORS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Number of Jurors; Alternate. There shall be six jurors chosen to hear a case plus the Court may allow one additional juror to be chosen as an alternate juror. In the event that an alternate juror is chosen and hears the case, he shall be dismissed prior to the jury's deliberation if not needed and treated like a regular juror if needed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Examination of Jurors. The court shall permit the parties or the attorneys to conduct the examination of prospective jurors and may itself examine the jurors.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Challenges.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A challenge is an objection made to a potential trial juror. Either party may challenge jurors but where there are several parties on each side, they must agree to join in a challenge before it can be made.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Challenges to jurors are either peremptory or for cause. Each party or side shall be entitled to three peremptory challenges.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Challenges for cause shall be made against a potential juror on the grounds that he is not entitled or qualified to be a juror, he is familiar with the case or has formed an opinion regarding the case, or if for any other reason it appears likely or reasonably possible that a juror will not be able to render a fair, impartial verdict. The judge may take evidence relative to a challenge for cause and shall in any event render a decision thereon.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Selection of Jury. The Clerk shall draw lots to determine potential jurors and shall replace jurors for whom a challenge is sustained until a full panel is completed. Upon completion, the clerk shall administer the oath to the jurors, the form of which shall be prescribed by rule of the Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Discharge of Juror. If, after the proceedings begin and before a verdict is reached, a juror becomes unable or disqualified to perform his duty, the alternate juror shall take his place; if there is no alternate juror, the parties may agree to complete the action with the other jurors. If no agreement can be reached, the judge shall discharge the jury and the case shall be tried with a new jury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>View of Jury. The Court may, for good cause shown allow the jury to view the property or place of occurrence of a disputed or otherwise relevant event.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Separation of the Jury. Any time prior to their verdict when the jurors are allowed to leave the courtroom, the judge shall admonish them not to converse with or listen to any other person on the subject of the trial and further admonish them not to form or express an opinion on the case until the case is submitted to the jury for their decision.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Deliberation. Once the case is submitted to them, the jury shall retire to deliberate in private under the charge of an officer of the court who will refrain from communicating with them except to inquire whether they have reached a verdict, and he shall prevent others from improperly communicating with the jury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Things Taken by Jury. The jury may take with them when deliberating any of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>the Court's instructions.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>papers or things received in evidence as exhibits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>notes taken by the jurors themselves, but not notes taken by a non-juror.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>Additional Instructions. If after the jury retires, there is some question on an instruction or other point of law or disagreement regarding the testimony, the jury may request additional instructions from the Court, such to be given on the record after notice to the parties or their counsel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>. 	No Verdict. If the jury is discharged before rendering their verdict or for any reason prevented from giving a verdict, the action shall be retried.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>Declaration of the Verdict. When at least five all or of the six jury members agree on a verdict, they shall so inform the officer who shall notify the Court. A unanimous verdict shall be required in criminal trial. The jury shall be conducted into the courtroom, the clerk shall call the jury roll; the verdict shall be given in writing to the clerk and then read by the clerk to the court; inquiry shall be made by the court to the jury foreman as to whether such is their verdict. Either party may have the jury polled individually to determine if such is, in fact, their verdict. If insufficient jurors agree with the verdict, the jury shall be sent out again to reconsider; otherwise, the verdict is complete and the jury shall be dismissed. If the verdict is read or recorded incorrectly by the clerk or foreman, the jury shall retire to correct the verdict.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|20" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.210</num>
      <heading>SPECIAL VERDICTS AND INTERROGATORIES.</heading>
      <text>The court may require the jury to return their verdict in the form of specific findings on specified issues or may require the jury to return a general verdict accompanied by answers to questions related to the issue under consideration.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|21" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.220</num>
      <heading>INSTRUCTIONS TO THE JURY; ARGUMENTS,</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Instructions. At the close of the evidence or at such earlier time as the Court may direct, any party may file written requested instructions for the court to give the jury. The court shall inform the parties or their counsel of the instructions It intends to give and hear argument thereon out of the hearing of the jury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Arguments. Final arguments for the parties shall be made after the jury has been instructed. The court shall not comment on the evidence of the case and, if it should restate any of the evidence, it shall inform the jury that they are the sole judges of the facts.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|22" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.230</num>
      <heading>MOTIONS FOR DIRECTED VERDICT AND FOR JUDGMENT NOTWITHSTANDING THE VERDICT.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Motion for a Directed Verdict. A party who moves for a directed verdict at the close of the evidence offered by the opposing side may offer evidence as if no motion had been made in the event that the motion is denied. A motion for directed verdict shall state the grounds therefore and may be granted by the court without the assent of the jury.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Motion for Judgment Notwithstanding the Verdict. A party who has made a motion or a directed verdict at the close of all the evidence, which motion has been denied or not granted, may, within 10 days after entry of judgment move to have the verdict and any judgment entered thereon set aside and entered according to his motion for directed verdict; or if there has been verdict, the party may so move within 10 days after the jury has been discharged. A motion for a new trial may be made in the alternative. The court shall enter judgment or make any orders consistent with his decision on the motion.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|23" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.240</num>
      <heading>FINDINGS BY THE COURT.</heading>
      <text>In cases tried without a jury, and except in cases where a party defaults, fails to appear or otherwise waives such, findings of fact and conclusions of law shall be made by the court in support of all final judgments. Upon its own motion or the motion of any party within ten days of the entry of judgment, findings may be amended or added to and the judgment may be amended accordingly.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|24" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.250</num>
      <heading>JUDGMENT: COSTS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Definition. A judgment includes any final order from which an appeal is available and no special form of judgment is required.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Judgment on Multiple Claims. When more than one claim for relief is presented in an action, however designated, a final judgment may be entered on less than all of such claims only upon the Court's specifically finding that such is justified. Absent such a finding, an order or decision will not terminate the action as to any of the claims until all claims are finally decided, nor will the appeal period commence to run.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Demand for Judgment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Generally. Except in the case of a default judgment, every final judgment shall grant the relief to which the party in whose favor it is rendered is entitled, even if such relief is not demanded in the pleadings. It may be given for or against one or more of several claimants; and it may, if justice so requires, determine the ultimate rights of the parties on each side as between or among themselves.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Judgment by Default. A judgment by default shall not be different in kind from, or exceed in amount, that specifically prayed for in the demand for judgment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Costs. Unless the court shall otherwise direct, the court shall allow necessary costs and disbursements to the prevailing party or parties as a matter of course. Such prevailing party shall file with the court a verified memorandum of his costs and necessary disbursements within five (5) days of the entry of judgment and serve a copy of such on the opposing party, and if such are not objected to within 10 days, they shall be deemed to be a part of and included in the judgment rendered. The Supreme Court may award costs in a like manner. Costs shall not be awarded against the Kiowa Tribe by either the trial or Supreme Court without the consent of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Attorney Fees. The court shall not award attorney fees in a case unless such have been specifically provided for by a contract or agreement of the parties under dispute, or unless it reasonably appears that the case has been prosecuted for purposes of harassment only, or that there was no reasonable expectation of success on the part of the affirmatively claiming party.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|25" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.260</num>
      <heading>DEFAULT.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Entry of Default. When a party against whom a judgment for affirmative relief is sought has failed to plead or otherwise defend as provided by these rules, his default may be entered by the clerk and judgment by default granted. Once the default is entered no further notice to the defaulting party of any action taken or to be taken need be given.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Judgment by Default. Judgment by default may be entered by the clerk if a party's claim against the opposing party is for a sum of money which is or can by computation be made certain, and if the opposing party has been personally served on the reservation. Otherwise, judgment by default can be entered only by the court upon receipt of whatever evidence the court deems necessary to establish the claim. No judgment by default shall be entered against the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Setting Aside Default. The court may, for good cause shown set aside either an entry of default improperly entered or entered against the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|26" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.270</num>
      <heading>SUMMARY JUDGMENT.</heading>
      <text>Anytime 20 days after commencement of an action, any party may move the court for summary judgment as to any or all of the issues presented in the case and such shall be granted by the court if it appears that there is no genuine issue as to any material fact and that the moving party is entitled to judgment as a matter of law.</text>
      <text>Such motions, which shall be served not less than 10 days prior to the hearing on said motion, may be supported by affidavits, discovery, or memoranda, all of which must be made available to opposing parties at least two days prior to the hearing.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|27" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.280</num>
      <heading>ENTRY OF JUDGMENT.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Judgment. Judgment upon verdict of a jury shall be signed by the clerk and filed. All other judgments shall be signed by the judge and filed with the clerk.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Effectiveness; Recordation. A judgment is complete and shall be deemed entered for all purposes when it is signed and filed as provided herein. The clerk shall immediately make a notation of the judgment in the register of actions and the judgment docket.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Death of a party. If a party dies after a verdict or decision upon any issue of fact and before judgment, judgment may nevertheless be entered thereon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Satisfaction of Judgment. A judgment may be satisfied, in whole or in part, as to any or all of the judgment debtors by the owner thereof or his attorney of record executing under oath and filing an acknowledgment of satisfaction specifying the amount paid and whether such is a full or partial satisfaction. A judge may order the entry of satisfaction upon proof of payment and failure of the judgment creditor to file a satisfaction. The clerk shall file all satisfactions of judgment and note the amount thereof in the register of actions and the judgment docket.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Effect of Satisfaction; Limitation. A judgment satisfied in whole, with such act being entered in the judgment docket, shall cease to operate as such. A partially satisfied judgment or unsatisfied judgment shall continue in effect for eight (8) years or until satisfied. An action to renew the judgment remaining unsatisfied may be maintained any time prior to the expiration of eight (8) years and will extend the period of limitations an additional 8 years and may be thereafter further extended by the same procedure.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|28" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.290</num>
      <heading>NEW TRIALS: AMENDMENTS OF JUDGMENT.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Grounds; Time. Any party may petition for a new trial on any or all of the issues presented by serving a motion not later than 10 days after the entry of judgment for any of the following causes:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>error or irregularity which prevented any party from receiving a fair trial; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>misconduct of the jury or jury members; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>accident or surprise, or newly discovered evidence which ordinary prudence could not have guarded against or produced at trial; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>damages so excessive or inadequate that they appear to have been</text>
          <text>given under influence of passion or prejudice; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>insufficiency of the evidence to justify the verdict or other decision, or that it is against the law; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>error in law.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Harmless Error. A new trial shall not be granted on the basis of error irregularity that was harmless in that It did not affect substantial justice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Support for Motion. Parties may include memoranda or affidavits in support of their motions to which reply memoranda and affidavits shall be allowed if desired.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Court Initiative. The court may, on its own initiative, not later than 10 days after entry of judgment, order a new trial on any grounds assertible by a party to the action, and shall specify the reasons for so ordering.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Motion to Alter or Amend Judgment. A motion to alter or amend a judgment shall be served not later than 10 days after entry of the judgment.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|29" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.300</num>
      <heading>RELIEF FROM JUDGMENT OR ORDER.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Clerical Mistakes. Clerical mistakes in judgments, orders or other parts of the record and errors herein arising from oversight or omission may be corrected by the court at any time of its own initiative or on the motion of any party and after such notice as the court may direct; mistakes may be corrected before an appeal is docketed in the Supreme Court, and thereafter while the appeal is pending may be corrected with leave of the Supreme Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Mistakes; Inadvertence; Excusable Neglect; Newly Discovered Evidence; Fraud, etc. On motion and upon such terms as are just, the court may, in the furtherance of justice, relieve a party or his legal representative from a final. judgment, order, or proceeding for the following reasons: (1) mistake, inadvertence, surprise, or excusable neglect; (2) newly discovered evidence which by due diligence could not have been discovered in time to move for a new trial under <cite path="|5.03.300">this section</cite>; (3) fraud, misrepresentation or other misconduct of an adverse party; (4) when, for any cause, the summons in an action has not been personally served upon the defendant and the defendant has failed to appear in said action; (5) the judgment is void; (6) the judgment has been satisfied, released, or discharged, or a judgment upon which it is based has been reversed or otherwise vacated, or it is no longer equitable that the judgment should have prospective application; or (7) any other reason justifying relief from the operation of the judgment. The motion shall be made with a reasonable time and for reasons (1), (2), (3), or (4), not more than 3 months after the judgment, order, or proceeding was entered or taken. A motion under this subdivision (b) does not affect the finality of a judgment or suspend its operation. <cite path="|5.03.300">This section</cite> does not limit the power of a court to entertain an independent action to relieve a party from a judgment, order or proceeding or to set aside a judgment for fraud upon the court. The procedure for obtaining any relief from a judgment shall be by motion as prescribed in these rules or by an independent action.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|30" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.310</num>
      <heading>HARMLESS ERROR.</heading>
      <text>No error in either the admission or the exclusion of evidence, and no error or defect in any ruling or order or in anything done or omitted by the court or by any of the parties, is ground for granting a new trial or otherwise disturbing a judgment or order, unless refusal to take such action appears to the court inconsistent with substantial justice. The court at every stage of the proceeding shall disregard any error or defect in the proceeding that does not affect the substantial rights of the parties.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|31" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.320</num>
      <heading>STAY OF PROCEEDINGS TO ENFORCE A JUDGMENT.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Stay Upon Entry of Judgment. Proceedings to enforce a judgment may issue immediately upon the entry of the judgment, unless the court in its discretion and on such conditions for the security of the adverse party as are proper, otherwise directs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Stay on Motion for New Trial or for Judgment. In its discretion and on such conditions for the security of the adverse party as are proper, the court may stay the execution of, or any proceedings to enforce, a judgment pending the disposition of a motion for a new trial or to alter or amend a judgment or of a motion for relief from a judgment or order, or of a motion for judgment in accordance with a motion for a directed verdict, or of a motion for amendment to the findings or for additional findings.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Injunction Pending Appeal. When an appeal is taken from an interlocutory or final judgment granting, dissolving, or denying an injunction, the court in its discretion may suspend, modify, restore, or grant an injunction during the pendency of the appeal upon such conditions as it considers proper for the security of the rights of the adverse party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Stay Upon Appeal. When an appeal is taken the appellant by giving a supersedeas bond in an amount set by the court may obtain a stay, unless such a stay is otherwise required or prohibited by law or by these rules. The bond may be given at or within 10 days after the time of filing the notice of appeal. The stay is effective when the bond is paid to the court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Stay in Favor or the Tribe, or Agency Thereof. When an appeal is taken by the Tribe, or an officer or agency of the Tribe in an official capacity, the operation or enforcement of the judgment is automatically stayed, and no bond, obligation, or other security shall be required from the appellant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Power of Supreme Court Not Limited. The provisions in <cite path="|5.03.320">this section</cite> do not limit any power of the Supreme Court or of a judge or justice thereof to stay proceedings during the pendency of an appeal or to suspend, modify, restore, or grant an injunction during the pendency of an appeal or to make any order appropriate to preserve the status quo or the effectiveness of the judgment subsequently to be entered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Stay of Judgment upon Multiple Claims. When a court has ordered a final judgment on some but not all of the claims presented in the action under the conditions stated in Rule 25, the court may stay enforcement of that judgment until the entering of a subsequent judgment or judgments and may prescribe such conditions as are necessary to secure the benefit thereof to the party in whose favor the judgment is entered.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Waiver of Undertaking. In all cases, the parties may, by written stipulation, waive the requirements of <cite path="|5.03.320">this section</cite> with respect to the filing of a bond or undertaking. In all cases where an undertaking is required by these rules a deposit in court in the amount of such undertaking, or such lesser amount as the court may order, is equivalent to the filing of the undertaking.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|32" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.330</num>
      <heading>DISABILITY OR DISQUALIFICATION OF A JUDGE.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Disability. If by reason of death, sickness, or other disability, a judge before whom an action has been tried is unable to perform the duties to be performed by the court under these rules after a verdict is returned or findings of fact and conclusions of law are filed, then any other judge regularly sitting in or assigned to the court may perform those duties; but if such other judge is satisfied that he cannot perform those duties because he did not preside at the trial or for any other reason, he may in his discretion grant a new trial.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Disqualification. Whenever a party to any action or proceedings, civil or criminal, or his attorney shall make and file an affidavit that the judge before whom such action or proceeding is to be tried or hear has a bias or prejudice, either against such party or his attorney or in favor of any opposite party to the suit, such judge shall proceed no further therein, except to call in another judge to hear and determine the matter.</text>
        <text>Every such affidavit shall state the facts and the reasons for the belief that such bias or prejudice exists and shall be filed as soon as practicable after the case has been assigned or such bias or prejudice is known. If the judge against whom the affidavit is directed questions the sufficiency of the affidavit, he shall enter an order directing that a copy thereof be forthwith certified to another judge (naming him), which judge shall then pass upon the legal sufficiency of the affidavit. If the judge against whom the affidavit is directed does not question the legal sufficiency of the affidavit, or if the judge to whom the affidavit is certified finds that it is legally sufficient, another judge must be called in to try the case or to determine the matter in question. No party shall be entitled in any case to file more than one affidavit; and no such affidavit shall be filed unless accompanied by a certificate of counsel of record that such affidavit and application are made in good faith.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|33" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.340</num>
      <heading>INJUNCTIONS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Preliminary Injunction; Notices. No preliminary injunction shall be issue without notice to the adverse party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Temporary Restraining Order; Notice; Rehearing; Duration. No temporary restraining order shall be granted without notice to the adverse party unless it clearly appears from specific facts shown by affidavit or by the verified complaint that immediate and irreparable injury, loss, or damage will result to the applicant before notice can be served and a hearing had thereon. Every temporary restraining order granted without notice shall be endorsed with the date and hour of issuance; and shall be filed forthwith in the clerk's office and entered of record; shall define the injury and state why it is irreparable and why the order was granted without notice; and shall expire by its terms within such time after entry, not to exceed 15 days, as the court fixes, unless within the time so fixed the order, for good cause shown, is extended for a like period or unless the party against whom the order is directed consents that it may be extended for a longer period. The reasons for the extension shall be entered of record. In case a temporary restraining order is granted without notice, the motion for a preliminary injunction shall be set down for hearing at the earliest possible time and takes precedence over all matters except older matters of the same character; and when the motion comes on for hearing the party who obtained the temporary restraining order shall proceed with the application for a preliminary injunction and, if he does not do so, the court shall dissolve the temporary restraining order. On 2 days notice to the party who obtained the temporary restraining order without notice or on such shorter notice to that party as the court may prescribe, the adverse party may appear and move its dissolution or modification and in that event the court shall proceed to hear and determine such motion as expeditiously as the ends of justice require.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Security. Except as otherwise provided by law, no restraining order or preliminary injunction shall issue except upon the giving of security by the applicant, in such sum as the court deems proper, for the payment of such costs and damages as may be incurred or suffered by any party who is found to have been wrongfully enjoined or restrained. No such security shall be required of the United States, the Kiowa Tribe, or of an officer, or agency, of either acting in an official capacity; nor shall it be required of a married person in a suit against the other party to the marriage contract.</text>
        <text>A surety upon a bond or undertaking under <cite path="|5.03.340">this section</cite> submits himself to the jurisdiction of the court and irrevocably appoints the clerk of the court as his agent upon whom any papers affecting his liability on the bond or undertaking may be served. His liability may be enforced on motion without the necessity of an independent action. The motion and such notice of the motion as the court prescribes may be served on the clerk of the court who shall forthwith mail copies to the persons giving the security if their addresses are known.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Form and Scope of Injunction or Restraining Order; Service. Every order granting an injunction and every restraining order shall be specific in terms; shall describe in reasonable detail, and not by reference to the complaint or other document, the act or acts sought to be restrained; and is binding only upon the parties to the action, their officers, agents, servants, employees, and attorneys, and upon those persons in active concert or participation with them who receive actual notice of the order by personal service or otherwise.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Grounds for Injunction. An injunction may be granted:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>When it appears by the pleadings on file that a party is entitled to the relief demanded, and such relief, or any part thereof, consists in restraining the commission or continuance of some act complained of, either for a limited period or perpetually.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>When it appears from the pleadings or by affidavit that the commission or continuance of some act during the litigation would produce great or irreparable injury to the party seeking injunctive relief.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>When it appears during the litigation that either party is doing or threatens, or is about to do, or is procuring or suffering to be done, some act of violation of the rights of another party respecting the subject matter of the action, and tending to render the judgment ineffectual.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>In all other cases where an injunction would be proper in equity. Rule</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|34" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.350</num>
      <heading>EXTRAORDINARY WRITS.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Grounds for Relief. Where no other plain, speedy and adequate remedy exists, relief may be obtained by obtaining an extraordinary writ that may be granted for any one of the following grounds:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Where any person usurps, intrudes into, or unlawfully holds or exercises a public office or does or permits to be done any act which by law works a forfeiture of his office; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Where an inferior tribunal, board or officer exercising judicial functions has exceeded its jurisdiction or abused its discretion; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Where the relief sought is to compel any inferior tribunal, board or person to perform an act which the law specially enjoins as a duty resulting from an office, trust or station; or to compel the admission of a party to the use and enjoyment of a right or office to which he is entitled and from which he is excluded by such inferior tribunal, board or person; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Where the relief sought is to arrest the proceedings of any tribunal, board or person, whether exercising functions judicial or ministerial, when such proceedings are without or in excess of the jurisdiction of such tribunal, board, or person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Habeas Corpus. Appropriate relief by habeas corpus proceedings shall be granted whenever it appears to the court that any person is unjustly imprisoned or otherwise unjustly restrained of his liberty. Upon the filing of the complaint the court shall, unless it appears from such complaint or the showing of the plaintiff that he is not entitled to any relief, issue a writ directed to the defendant commanding him to bring the person alleged to be restrained before the court at a time and place therein specified, at which time the Court shall proceed in a summary manner to hear the matter and render judgment accordingly. If the writ is not issued, the court shall state its reasons in writing and file the same with the complaint and shall deliver a copy thereof to the plaintiff. If the defendant cannot be found, or if he does not have such person in custody, the writ (and any other process issued) may be served upon any one having such person in custody, in the manner and with the same effect as if he had been made defendant. in the action.</text>
        <text>The defendant shall appear at the proper time and place with the person designated or show good cause for not doing so and must answer the complaint within the time allowed. The answer must state plainly and unequivocally whether he then has, or at any time has had the person designated under this control and restraint, and if so, the cause thereof. If such person has been transferred, the defendant must state that fact, and to whom, when the transfer was made, and the reason or authority therefor. The writ shall not be disobeyed for any defect of form or mis-description of the person restrained or the defendant, if enough is stated to show the meaning and intent thereof.</text>
        <text>The person restrained may waive his right to be present at the hearing, in which case the writ shall be modified accordingly. Pending a determination of the matter the court may place such person in the custody of such individual or individuals as may be deemed proper.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Habeas Corpus; Decision. In each case, the court, upon determining the case, shall enter specific findings of fact and conclusions of law and judgment, in writing, and the same shall be made a part of the record in the case. If the court finds in favor of the complainant, it shall enter an appropriate order with respect to judgment or sentence in the former proceedings and such further orders with respect to re- arraignment, retrial, custody, bail, or discharge as the court may deem just and proper in the case.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Habeas Corpus Availability. Except in cases of extraordinary injustice, habeas corpus relief shall not be available to a person incarcerated as a result of a criminal conviction where the alleged grounds for relief have been or could have been raised by an appeal following the conviction.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|35" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.360</num>
      <heading>EXECUTION.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Time. If within 60 days after entry of a judgment awarding money damages and/or costs against a party, or within 60 days after final resolution of an appeal to the Supreme Court from such a judgment, it is made to appear to the court that the judgment debtor has not paid the judgment amount in full or commenced making installment payments in a manner agreed to by the parties, or is not current in such payments, the Court shall upon motion of the judgment creditor heard ex parte, order the Kiowa Tribal Police to execute on the personal property of the judgment debtor as provided herein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Procedure. The court shall order the judgment debtor to appear before it and answer under oath regarding all his personal property. The court shall then determine what property of the judgment debtor is available for execution and order the Kiowa Tribal Police to seize as much of such property as reasonably appears necessary to pay the judgment amount. Failure of the judgment debtor to appear may be deemed a contempt of court and the court may proceed without such appearance. Sale of the seized property shall be at public auction conducted by the Kiowa Tribal Police after giving at least 10 days public notice posted in at least three conspicuous places within the Territory of the Tribe. Property shall be sold to the highest bidder who shall make payment for the property at the time of sale. The person conducting the auction may postpone such in his discretion if there is inadequate response to the action or the bidding and may reschedule such upon giving the required notice.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Exemption from Execution. The Court shall only order seizure and sale of such property of the judgment debtor to satisfy a money judgment the loss of which will not impose an immediate substantial hardship on the immediate family of the judgment debtor. Only property of the judgment debtor himself may be subject to execution and not property of his family.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Redemption from Sale. At any time within 6 months after sale under <cite path="|5.03.360">this section</cite>, the judgment debtor may redeem his property from the purchases thereof by paying the amount such purchaser paid for the property plus 8 percent interest, plus any expense actually incurred by the purchaser, such as taxes and insurance, to maintain the property.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|36" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.370</num>
      <heading>APPEAL.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Supreme Court. All appeals from the Kiowa Trial Court shall be heard by the Kiowa Supreme Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Right to Appeal. Any party who is aggrieved by any final order, commitment or judgment of the trial court may appeal in the manner prescribed by <cite path="|5.03.370">this section</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Time; Notice of Appeal. Within 20 days from the entry of the order of judgment appealed from the party taking the appeal must file with the trial court a written notice of appeal specifying the parties to the appeal, the order or judgment appealed from, and a short statement of the reason or grounds for the appeal. The clerk shall file the notice and mail copies, to be provided by the appealing party, to all other parties to the appeal at their last known address.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Parties. The party taking the appeal shall be referred to as the appellant; all other parties shall be referred to as the respondent. The name of the case shall be the same as that used in the trial court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Bond on Appeal. At the time of filing the Notice of Appeal, the appellant shall also file cash or a surety bond in an amount set by the trial court sufficient to guarantee performance of the judgment if such performance is stayed on appeal plus, in any event, sufficient to guarantee payment of such costs or interest as the Supreme Court may award.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Stay Pending Appeal. In any case in which an appeal is perfected as required by <cite path="|5.03.370">this section</cite>, the appellant may petition the trial court for an order staying the order, commitment or judgment rendered conditioned upon execution of a bond to guarantee performance of the judgment, order or commitment. A stay shall begranted in all cases in which it is requested unless manifest injustice would result therefrom.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Clerk. The Clerk of the Trial Court shall also serve as the Clerk of the Supreme Court. Within 5 days after a Notice or Appeal is filed, the Clerk shall prepare, certify and file with the Supreme Court all papers comprising the record of the case appealed. A separate docket shall be maintained for the Supreme Court in which shall be recorded each stage of the proceedings on each case appealed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Subpoenas. The presiding judge of the Supreme Court shall, when hearing a case, have authority by subpoena to compel a witness to attend and testify or compel the production of documents where such is deemed necessary to the rendition of the court's opinion. There shall not, however, be a new trial in the appellate court, and, except in cases where the findings of fact of the trial court are clearly erroneous, there will be no review of the factual findings of the trial court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Briefs and Memoranda. Within 30 days of the filing of the Notice of Appeal or within such longer time as the Supreme Court shall allow, the appellant shall file a written brief, memorandum, or statement in support of his appeal. An original and two copies shall be filed with the clerk and one additional copy shall be served upon or mailed to each other party or his attorney. The respondent shall have 20 days after receipt of the appellant's brief, memorandum or statement and shall file and serve such in the same manner as the appellant's brief, memorandum, or statement. No further response shall be allowed either party without leave of court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>Argument. The Supreme Court shall decide all cases upon the briefs, memoranda and statements filed plus the record of the trial court without oral argument unless either party requests oral argument and shows to the court that such will be likely to aid the court's decision, or unless the court decides on its own motion to hear oral argument.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>Decision. The Supreme Court shall issue a written decision and all judgments on appeal which shall be final unless federal law or regulations provide for further extra- Tribal remedies.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|37" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.380</num>
      <heading>CITATION.</heading>
      <text>These Rules shall be known as the Kiowa Rules of Civil Procedure and may be abbreviated K.R.C.P.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|38" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.390</num>
      <heading>FEES.</heading>
      <text>The Chief Judge of the Trial Court, under recommendation of the Clerk of the Court, shall, from time to time, set a schedule of fees. Under no circumstances may the fee for an Order of Protection be more than ten dollars ($10). Thirty days prior to the fee schedule going into effect, the Chief Judge shall give notice to the Tribal Legislature and Council that a new schedule is going into effect and provide a copy of the schedule.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|39" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <prefix></prefix>
      <num>5.03.400</num>
      <heading>USE AND APPLICATION OF FEDERAL AND STATE RULES.</heading>
      <text>To the extent that it is found that certain necessary court procedures and laws have not been adequately addressed in the Kiowa Tribal District Court Rules, the Kiowa Tribal Code of Civil Procedure or by the Kiowa Tribal Law &amp; Order Code, the Kiowa Judiciary may draw upon the Federal Rules of Civil and Criminal Procedure, as well as the Local Court Rules of the United States District Court for the Western District of Oklahoma for guidance and application as in the discretion of the Kiowa Judiciary will best serve the efficient and timely dispensing of justice. Only upon a finding that a such void in the Kiowa Codes and Rules is not adequately addressed by the federal rules, may the Kiowa Judiciary then look to employ the Oklahoma Criminal, Civil and Appellate Procedures.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2017-07-18" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-008" eff="2017-07-18" path="attachments|law|II|40" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.04</num>
    <heading>Model Rules of Judicial Conduct</heading>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.05</num>
    <heading>Judiciary</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.05.010</num>
      <text>The Justices of the Supreme Court may select any person licensed to practice law in the United States, to serve as a "<em>Judge pro-tem</em>" of the Trial court, until the Justices of the Supreme Court determine a <em>pro-tem</em> appointment is no longer necessary; and,</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-01-19" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2023-002" eff="2023-01-19" path="attachments|law|1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.05.020</num>
      <text>The Chief Justice of the Supreme Court shall be responsible for managing or delegating the management of the dockets of all Courts in the Judicial Branch.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2023-01-19" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2023-002" eff="2023-01-19" path="attachments|law|2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>5.06</num>
    <heading>Full Faith and Credit</heading>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.010</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="|5.06">This chapter</cite> shall be known as the "Establishment for Recognition of Judicial Proceedings in Foreign Courts-Full Faith and Credit".</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.1" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.020</num>
      <heading>Official Seals of the Courts of the Kiowa Tribe</heading>
      <text>The court of original jurisdiction for the Kiowa Tribe is the Trial Court of the Kiowa Tribe. The court of appellate jurisdiction for the Kiowa Tribe is the Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe. To ensure the authenticity of official documents of said courts, the Court Clerks for each court shall ensure that the official seals for each court clearly state "Trial Court of the Kiowa Tribe" and "Supreme Court of the Kiowa Tribe" respectively.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.2" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.030</num>
      <heading>Definitions and Recitals</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Domestic Foreign Court" means any court or constitutionally established tribunal of the United States of America, any state, commonwealth, or territory of the United States of America, or any federally recognized Indian nation, tribe, pueblo, band, or Alaska Native village, duly established under federal law or tribal law, including Courts of Indian Offenses organized pursuant to Title 25, Part 11 of the Code of Federal Regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Judicial Officer" means any judge, justice, magistrate or other officer duly seated and authorized under federal, state, or tribal law to resolve disputes and enter judgments in a Domestic Foreign Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Domestic Foreign Judgment" means any final written judgment, decree or order of a trial court duly signed by a judicial officer and filed in a Domestic Foreign Court.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.3" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.040</num>
      <heading>Recognition of Domestic Foreign Judgements-Full Faith and Credit</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Trial Court of the Kiowa Tribe shall grant full faith and credit and cause to be enforced any Domestic Foreign Judgment where the Domestic Foreign Court that issued the judgment grants reciprocity to judgments of the courts of the Kiowa Tribe, provided, a Domestic Foreign Judgment shall receive no greater effect or full faith and credit under <cite path="|5.06.040">this section</cite> than would a similar or comparable judgment of any other Domestic Foreign Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>To the extent that a Domestic Foreign Court requires the Kiowa Tribe to grant reciprocity to judgments from the Domestic Foreign Court before granting reciprocity in return, the Trial Court Clerk is authorized to provide any documentation, whether in the form of a copy of this ordinance or in a certification from the court clerk's office, to the Domestic Foreign Court to secure said grant of reciprocity.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.4" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.050</num>
      <heading>Listing of Domestic Foreign Courts Granting Reciprocity</heading>
      <text>A list of the Domestic Foreign Courts that grant full faith and credit to the courts of the Kiowa Tribe shall be maintained by the Trial Court Clerk. Any Domestic Foreign Court may provide the Trial Court Clerk a copy of the ordinance, statute, court rule or other evidence that demonstrates that the Domestic Foreign Court grants reciprocity to the courts of the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.5" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.060</num>
      <heading>Filing of Domestic Foreign Judgements</heading>
      <text>A copy of any Domestic Foreign Judgment authenticated in accordance with the applicable act of Congress or of the statutes of this state or the law of the tribe may be filed in the office of the Trial Court Clerk of Kiowa Tribe. The Trial Court Clerk shall treat the Domestic Foreign Judgment in the same manner as a judgment of the Trial Court the Kiowa Tribe which may be enforced or satisfied in like manner.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.6" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.070</num>
      <heading>Notice of Filing</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>At the time of the filing of the Domestic Foreign Judgment with the Trial Court Clerk, the party filing the judgment or that party's attorney shall make and file with the Trial Court Clerk an affidavit setting forth the name and last-known address of all parties in the action, including the name and last-known address of any party's attorney.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Promptly upon the filing of the Domestic Foreign Judgment and the affidavit, the Trial Court Clerk shall mail notice of the filing of the Domestic Foreign Judgment to the party against whom the judgment was rendered at the address given and shall make a note of the mailing in the docket. The notice shall include the name and address of the party filing the judgment, and that party's attorney, if any. In addition, the party filing the judgment shall mail a notice of the filing of the judgment to the party against whom judgment was rendered and shall file an affidavit proving the mailing of the notice with the Trial Court Clerk within ten (10) days of the date that the Domestic Foreign Judgment was filed with the Trial Court Clerk. Failure of the Trial Court Clerk to mail the notice of filing of the judgment shall not affect the enforcement proceedings if an affidavit proving the mailing of the notice has been filed by the party filing the judgment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>No execution or other process for enforcement of a Domestic Foreign Judgment filed hereunder shall issue until the affidavit proving the mailing of the notice has been filed with the Trial Court Clerk, and twenty (20) days have expired from the date the judgment was filed in the Trial Court.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.7" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>5.06.080</num>
      <heading>Approval and Enactment</heading>
      <text>The Legislature hereby approves and Enacts the "Establishment for Recognition of Judicial Proceedings in Foreign Courts-Full Faith and Credit Act of 2024".</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation app="2024-01-23" doc="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2024-001" eff="2024-01-23" path="attachments|law|1.8" type="History"/>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
