<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-017">
  <num>KL-CY-2017-017</num>
  <heading>Public Information and Legislative Publishing Act of 2017</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2017-08-22</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2017-08-12</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2017-017.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-017</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>At a duly called Session of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe held this 12th day of August 2017, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the Legislature is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(a) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> the 7 District Legislators serve as the Peoples' representatives to ensure that the Tribe's government acts in a transparent and responsible manner in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and laws of the Tribe; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text><cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> requires the Legislature to publish certain documents including proposed laws, Legislative Orders, votes of the Legislature, and to otherwise provide information to the public.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE IT BE IT RESOLVED;</conjunction>
      <text> that the Legislature hereby enacts the attached law entitled, "PUBLIC INFORMATION AND LEGISLATIVE PUBLISHING ACT OF 2017".</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution KL-CY-2017-017 was duly voted upon at a duly called Session IV of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe held this 12th day of August 2017, the following Resolution and Law were adopted, with a vote of ( 7 ) in favor, and ( 0 ) opposed, ( 0 ) abstaining, and ( 0 ) absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Kiowa Tribe Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe Legislature</strong>
    </text>
    <text>RESOLUTION NO KL-CY-2017-017</text>
    <text>
      <strong>SPONSOR: RENEE M. PLATA, SPEAKER OF THE KIOWA TRIBE LEGISLATURE</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>CO-SPONSOR(S): RHONDA J. AHHAITTY, SECRETARY OF THE KIOWA LEGISLATURE; ANITA ONCO-JOHNSON, LEGISLATOR; DAVE GEIMAUSADDLE, LEGISLATOR; RONALD C. POOLAW, LEGISLATOR</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Renee M. Plata,</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Ronald C. Poolaw, Sr.</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Dave Geimausaddle</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Anita L. Onco-Johnson</td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Modina M. Waters</td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Ben Lucero Hovakah-Wolf</td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. <strong>KL-CY-2017-017</strong> was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the <strong>15</strong><sup><strong>th</strong></sup> day of <strong>August 2017</strong>, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by the Constitution.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Rhonda J. Ahhaifty, Secretary</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe Legislature</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ] 	VETO	-	RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this __________ day of _______________, 2017.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Matthew Komalty, Chairman</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the __________ day of _______________, 2017.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ] 	NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Renee M. Plata, Speaker</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Ronald C. Poolaw, Sr.</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Dave Geimausaddle</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Anita L. Onco-Johnson</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Modina M. Waters</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>Ben Lucero Hovakah-Wolf</td>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution <strong>KL-CY-2017-017</strong> was duly voted upon at a duly called Session IV of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe held this <strong>12</strong><sup><strong>th</strong></sup> day of <strong>August 2017</strong>, the following Resolution and Law were adopted, with a vote of <strong>( 7 )</strong> in favor, and <strong>( 0 )</strong> opposed, <strong>( 0 )</strong> abstaining, and <strong>( 0 )</strong> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Kiowa Tribe Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe Legislature</strong>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
  <section>
    <num>1.1</num>
    <heading>Short Title</heading>
    <text><cite path="">This enactment</cite> shall be known as, the "PUBLIC INFORMATION AND LEGISLATIVE PUBLISHING ACT OF 2017" ("Act").</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.2</num>
    <heading>Findings.</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(a)</num>
      <text>The 7 District Legislators serve as the Peoples' representatives to ensure that the Tribe's government acts in a transparent and responsible manner in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and laws of the Tribe.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(b)</num>
      <text><cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">The Constitution</cite> requires the Legislature to publish certain documents including proposed laws, Legislative Orders, votes of the Legislature, and to otherwise provide information to the public;</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(c)</num>
      <text>Members of the Tribe live in all areas of the Tribe's Territory and outside the Tribe's Territory, and the use of modern forms of electronic communication to publish and receive information from the Tribe, including from the Legislature, is the most cost-effective method to comply with the publishing requirements of <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>.</text>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.3</num>
    <heading>Purpose.</heading>
    <text>The purpose of <cite path="">this Act</cite> is to authorize and direct the Information Technology Program and Personnel ("IT Personnel") to publish on the Tribe's official website documents and information provided by the Legislature including proposed laws (bills), Legislative Orders, records and tallies of the votes of the Legislature, proceeding of the Legislature including official Sessions and hearings, enacted laws, and other important information.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.4</num>
    <heading>Publication of Documents and Information from the Legislature.</heading>
    <text>In order to guarantee that the Members of the Tribe have timely access to the official publications of the Tribe including documents and other important information from the Legislature, the Legislature hereby authorizes and directs the IT Personnel to publish on the Tribe's official website all documents and information provided by the Legislature and that <em>includes a specific request to publish</em> ("Request To Publish") such documents and/or information. The Request To Publish may include proposed laws (bills), Legislative Orders, records and tallies of the votes of the Legislature, proceeding of the Legislature including official Sessions and hearings, enacted laws, and other important information.</text>
    <text>Upon receipt of a Request To Publish, the IT Personnel shall publish the documents and information in a timely manner without modification or alternation, and the documents and information shall remain published until the Legislature provides a specific, written request to discontinue such publication.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>1.5</num>
    <heading>Development of Website for the Legislative</heading>
    <text>The IT Personnel shall assist the Legislature with the development of a website for the purpose of communications with the public.</text>
  </section>
</document>
