<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-011">
  <num>KL-CY-2017-011</num>
  <heading>Kiowa Housing Authority Reform Act of 2017</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2017-08-22</effective>
    <history>
      <adopted>2017-08-12</adopted>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res" url="./adopted/KL-CY-2017-011.pdf">Kiowa Tribe Res. No. KL-CY-2017-011</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <text>At a duly called Session of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe held this 12th day of August 2017, the following Resolution and Law were adopted.</text>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> 	the Legislature is vested with the authority to pass laws and resolutions pursuant to <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(a) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>; and,</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS;</conjunction>
      <text> 	the Legislature has determined that it is in the best interests of the Tribe to reform the Kiowa Housing Authority to bring it into compliance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and laws of the Tribe for the benefit of the members of the Tribe and the delivery of housing services.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE IT BE IT RESOLVED;</conjunction>
      <text> that the Legislature hereby enacts the attached law entitled, "Kiowa Housing Authority Reform Act of 2017".</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution KL-CY-2017-11 was duly voted upon at a duly called Session IV of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe held this 12th day of August 2017, the following Resolution and Law were adopted, with a vote of ( 7 ) in favor, and ( 0 ) opposed, ( 0 ) abstaining, and ( 0 ) absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Kiowa Tribe Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe Legislature</strong>
    </text>
    <text>RESOLUTION NO KL-CY-2017-011</text>
    <text>
      <strong>SPONSOR: RENEE M. PLATA, SPEAKER OF THE KIOWA TRIBE LEGISLATURE</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>CO-SPONSOR(S): RHONDA J. AHHAITTY, SECRETARY OF THE KIOWA LEGISLATURE; ANITA ONCO-JOHNSON, LEGISLATOR; DAVE GEIMAUSADDLE, LEGISLATOR; RONALD C. POOLAW, LEGISLATOR</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Renee M. Plata,</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Ronald C. Poolaw, Sr.</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Dave Geimausaddle</td>
            <th>X</th>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Anita L. Onco-Johnson</td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Modina M. Waters</td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Ben Lucero Hovakah-Wolf</td>
            <th>x</th>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION AND LAW TO THE CHAIRMAN</b>
    </text>
    <text>Resolution No. KL-CY-2017-011 was presented to the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe on the <strong>15</strong><sup><strong>th</strong></sup> day of <strong>August 2017</strong>, pursuant to the <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 8(a)(iv) of the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>, and will become effective after signature by the Chairman or veto override by the Legislature, and as otherwise required by the Constitution.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe Legislature</strong>
    </text>
    <text>CHAIRMAN'S ACTION:</text>
    <text>[    ] 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>[    ] 	VETO	-	RETURNED TO LEGISLATURE WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this __________ day of _______________, 2017.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Matthew Komalty, Chairman</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe</strong>
    </text>
    <text>Presented by the Chairman to the Legislature on the __________ day of _______________, 2017.</text>
    <text>
      <b>LEGISLATURE'S ACTION:</b>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Override of Chairman's veto:</strong>
    </text>
    <text>[    ] 	YES</text>
    <text>[    ] 	NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>LEGISLATORS</th>
            <th>YES</th>
            <th>NO</th>
            <th>ABSTAIN</th>
            <th>ABSENT</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Renee M. Plata, Speaker</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Ronald C. Poolaw, Sr.</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Dave Geimausaddle</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Anita L. Onco-Johnson</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Modina M. Waters</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td data-text-align="justify">Ben Lucero Hovakah-Wolf</td>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="center"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
            <td proof="needed" data-text-align="justify"/>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>
      <b>C E R T I F I C A T I O N</b>
    </text>
    <text>The foregoing Resolution <strong>KL-CY-2017-011</strong> was duly voted upon at a duly called <strong>Session IV</strong> of the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe held this <strong>12</strong><sup><strong>th</strong></sup> day of <strong>August 2017</strong>, the following Resolution and Law were adopted, with a vote of <strong>( 7 )</strong> in favor, and <strong>( 0 )</strong> opposed, <strong>( 0 )</strong> abstaining, and <strong>( 0 )</strong> absent, pursuant to the authority vested in the Kiowa Tribe Legislature by <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe</cite>.</text>
    <text>
      <strong>Rhonda J. Ahhaitty, Secretary</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>of the Kiowa Tribe Legislature</strong>
    </text>
  </procedural-data>
  <attachment id="law">
    <section>
      <num>1.1</num>
      <heading>Short Title</heading>
      <text><cite path="attachments|law">This enactment</cite> shall be known as the "Kiowa Housing Authority Reform Act 2017" ("Act").</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.2</num>
      <heading>Definitions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Chairman" shall mean the Chairman of the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Constitution" means <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> approved by the voters of the Tribe and the BIA on May 5, 2017.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"DARKO" means Darko Affordable Housing Solutions, LLC.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"HUD" means the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"Kiowa Housing Authority" means the entity which operates out of the Housing Authority offices at 1701 East Central Boulevard, Anadarko, Oklahoma, 73005, and serves as a sub-recipient of certain HUD federal funds authorized by the Tribe and provided to DARKO as Tribe's Tribally-Designated Housing Entity, and which otherwise operates and manages, in whole or in part, the Tribe's housing programs and services, or any other housing programs or services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>"Legislature" means the Legislature of the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>"TDHE" means the tribally-designated housing entity.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>"Tribe" means the Kiowa Tribe.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.3</num>
      <heading>Purpose</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="attachments|law">this Act</cite> is to reform the Tribe's Housing Authority to bring it into compliance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and laws of the Tribe, to take full responsibility to assert the Tribe's sovereign authority to address the housing needs of Members of the Tribe, and to abolish the outdated method of subjecting the Tribe's sovereign status to the full or partial control of the State of Oklahoma by operating the Tribe's Housing Authority, in whole or in part, as a State Agency. The purpose of the Act is also to re- establish respect for the Tribe's government, the institutions of government, and <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite> and laws including the duty of the Tribe and its elected officials, as the People's representatives, to oversee and direct the establishment of a Department of Housing and the delivery of housing-related services.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.4</num>
      <heading>Findings</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In 1965, Oklahoma law established housing authorities for Indian tribes located within Oklahoma as State Agencies for the purpose of receiving federal housing funds ("State Agency Housing Authority") at a time when Indian tribes were not eligible to receive direct federal funding for housing programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>After federal law changed, tribes in Oklahoma, including the Kiowa Tribe, have applied for and have received federal HUD funds directly from the federal government without the need to administer such funds through Oklahoma's State Agency Housing Authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Tribe never addressed the confusion over the original State Agency Housing Authority called the Kiowa Housing Authority, and its assets and liabilities, and the Tribe's Housing Authority, which also operates and manages, either directly or as a sub-recipient, the Tribe's HUD funds and housing programs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Kiowa Housing Authority has been the subject of lengthy and expensive disputes, including litigation before the Oklahoma Supreme Court over the selection and authority of the Housing Authority Board of Commissioners.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The recent instability within the Tribe's government also contributed to the Tribe's and/or Kiowa Housing Authority's inability to properly manage and administer HUD funds, resulting in a sanction against the Tribe requiring the Tribe to repay HUD approximately seven million dollars ($7,000,000.00) in federal funds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>As a result of the improper management and administration of HUD funds, the Kiowa Housing Authority no longer receives any direct funding from HUD, rather, the Tribe has designated DARKO as a TDHE to receive the Tribe's HUD funds, and DARKO provides certain funds to the Kiowa Housing Authority as a sub-recipient.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The Kiowa Housing Authority has few, if any, State Agency Housing Authority assets or liabilities, as the Kiowa Housing Authority programmatic activities and services derive from its status as a sub-recipient of HUD funds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>The Tribe is not an irrelevant party in the provision of housing services to the Members of the Tribe, and in fact, the Tribe, and the Tribe's housing policies and laws are central to the provision of housing services to the Members of the Tribe, especially the Tribe's decision to request and receive HUD funding and to designate DARKO as the a TDHE.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.5</num>
      <heading>No Effect on Existing Contract</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Nothing in <cite path="attachments|law">this Act</cite> is intended to alter or amend any existing contract with DARKO.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>DARKO, as the Tribe's TDHE, shall provide the Chairman and Legislature with a written report on October 1st and April 1st of each year detailing to the status of the Tribe's HUD funds, all program and administrative expenditures including all fees and payments made to DARKO, and an overall assessment of the Tribe's housing programs and affairs.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.6</num>
      <heading>Establishment of the Department of Housing</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Department of Housing is hereby established and shall be located with the Executive branch of government in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VII, Section 1(c) of the Constitution</cite>. The Department of Housing shall include all housing programs, services, and housing entities of the Tribe including the Kiowa Housing Authority. The Kiowa Housing Authority shall be known as the Department of Housing and shall no longer be autonomous or semi-autonomous from the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Legislature hereby directs the Chairman to take any and all actions necessary to undertake, manage, and control the Kiowa Housing Authority, and to continue to provide housing programs for the benefit of the Members of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Department of Housing shall operate and manage any and all Housing and Housing-related programs of the Tribe in compliance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">the Constitution</cite>, laws, and budgets of the Tribe, and in compliance with all legal requirements that may be imposed as a condition of receiving HUD funds or any other funds.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>The Department of Housing shall take all steps necessary to prepare the Tribe and the Department to apply for and receive HUD funds and other funds directly from the funding sources upon the expiration of the current contract with DARKO so that DARKO will no longer be needed as the Tribe's tribally-designated housing entity; provided, that the Department of Housing may continue to contract with DARKO to provide limited and short-term consulting services as needed and as authorized by the Housing Commission.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.7</num>
      <heading>Establishment of Housing Commission</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The Housing Commission is hereby established and shall be located within the Executive branch of government in accordance with <cite doc="Constitution of the Kiowa Tribe">Article VI, Section 6(h) of the Constitution</cite>. The Housing Commission shall consist of five members selected upon nomination by the Chairman and confirmation by the Legislature.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Housing Commission shall have the authority to oversee and regulate the Department of Housing including establishing standards and procedures to operate the Department, and authorizing contracts for the Department including any local cooperative agreements for payments in lieu of taxes as authorized by HUD. The Housing Commission shall have the authority to select or terminate a Director of the Department of Housing, subject to approval of the Chairman; provided that, if the Chairman takes no action to approve the decision of the Housing Commission regarding a Director, then the decision of the Housing Commission shall be deemed approved. The Housing Commission shall have the authority to promulgate regulations governing the operation of the Department of Housing.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.8</num>
      <heading>Oklahoma Law Encourages Tribes to Manage Housing Programs</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Oklahoma law states in pertinent part, "In the interest of the sovereign power of federally recognized Indian tribes, economy of efforts, and the maintenance of cooperative relationships between the state and federally recognized Indian tribes, and in light of the above findings, the state hereby authorizes any federally recognized Indian tribe, band or nation for whose benefit a state agency housing authority was or may be created, to assume management and control of the state agency Indian housing authority and all its assets, as provided in <cite path="attachments|law|1.8">this section</cite>." <em>See</em>, 63 OS 1057 (2010).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Oklahoma law establishes a process for tribes to fully assume all management, assets, liabilities, and control of any State Agency Housing Authority designated for an Indian tribe by enacting a Resolution or law to undertake the management and control of the State Agency Housing Authority in accordance with the requirements of such law; and, (2) filing the Resolution or law with the Oklahoma Secretary of State, Oklahoma Attorney General, and with the appropriate County Clerk.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The Kiowa Housing Authority has not received any direct funding from HUD for some time, and the Kiowa Housing Authority does not currently receive any direct funding from HUD, i.e., any federal funds that the Kiowa Housing Authority receives comes from its status as a sub-recipient of HUD funds provided to DARKO.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Nothing in <cite path="attachments|law">this Act</cite> authorizes the Chairman or Department of Housing to request any additional lands to be taken into trust with the U.S. Bureau of Indian Affairs or to request any change in any tax status of any real property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>The Legislature hereby directs the Chairman to take any and all actions necessary to undertake, manage, and control the State Agency Housing Authority as may be required, including assuming both the assets and liabilities of the State Agency Housing Authority and the Kiowa Housing Authority, to continue to provide housing programs for the benefit of the Members of the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>1.9</num>
      <heading>Authorization of Appropriation of Funds</heading>
      <text>The Legislature hereby authorizes an appropriation of funds to be included in the Annual Budget or Budget Modification for expenditure to implement <cite path="attachments|law">this Act</cite>.</text>
    </section>
  </attachment>
</document>
